<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loves of Amandus and Sophronia, historically narrated a piece of rare contexture, inriched with many pleasing odes and sonnets, occasioned by the jocular or tragicall occurrences hapning in the progresse of the historie : disposed into three books or tracts / by Samuel Sheppard.</title>
            <author>Sheppard, S. (Samuel)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14694</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12719077</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12719077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 369:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loves of Amandus and Sophronia, historically narrated a piece of rare contexture, inriched with many pleasing odes and sonnets, occasioned by the jocular or tragicall occurrences hapning in the progresse of the historie : disposed into three books or tracts / by Samuel Sheppard.</title>
                  <author>Sheppard, S. (Samuel)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 140 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.D. for Iohn Hardestie ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page and p. 140 have print missing in filmed copy. Title page-15 and p. 130-end photographed from British Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The Loves OF AMANDUS AND SOPHRONIA, Hiſtorically Narrated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Piece of rare Contexture,</hi> Inriched with many pleaſing <hi>Odes</hi> and <hi>Sonnets,</hi> occaſioned by the Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, or Tragicall occurrences, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the progreſſe of the HISTORIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſpoſed into three Books, or Tracts By</hi> Samuel Sheppard.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Horace,</bibl>
               </p>
               <l>
                  <hi>—Quod fi meliora noviſti,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Candidus Imparti, ſi non, his utere mecum.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Hardeſtie,</hi> to be ſold at the <hi>Black Spred-Eagle</hi> in <hi>Ducklane,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:2"/>
            <head>LEt the Reader be pleaſed to Cenſure mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Printer, by whoſe overſight, are theſe <hi>Erratas.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>for</hi> Permitias <hi>read</hi> Premitias.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> Lunary <hi>read</hi> Luminary.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> Uronea <hi>read</hi> Pronea.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 73. <hi>for</hi> deſert <hi>read</hi> Diſſect. <hi>for</hi> Rapide <hi>r.</hi> Rabbide.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:2"/>
            <head>CANDIDO ET CORDATO</head>
            <p>Amico foelici Genio, perſpicaci, Ingenio, <hi>Iohan. Mane</hi> De(—) <hi>Baronetto</hi> Eoque titulo, vere digno</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SAMUEL SHEPPARD,</hi> hoſce extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos Amatorum Amplexus Animi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitias, Solenni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> officio perfunctas hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill</p>
            <p>ime.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dedit, Dicavit, Dedicavit.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Cloth-Faire, <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 20. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:3"/>
         </div>
         <div n="from J. Bourne" type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:3"/>
            <head>To the Author on his Excellent Romantick Piece.</head>
            <l>THe Priviledge that pens doe find</l>
            <l>'Mongſt men, comes ſhort unto the mind,</l>
            <l>For mentall Cabinets doe yeild</l>
            <l>No jot unto the Criticks ſhield:</l>
            <l>If thoughts might crown deſerts, I dare</l>
            <l>Give to my Pen the largeſt ſhare.</l>
            <l>But when our Vultures 'gin to gnaw,</l>
            <l>I'le ceaſe for feare, and ſay tis Law;</l>
            <l>Its better faile of debt, then be</l>
            <l>Honeſt, in tearms, of flattery;</l>
            <l>I hate the thought, I'le freely give</l>
            <l>My Verdict, which perhaps may live</l>
            <l>'Gainſt Calumnie. If Learning may</l>
            <l>With Wit, win Fame, thou haſt the day.</l>
            <l>Crown'd be thy brows with laſting Bayes,</l>
            <l>Who giv'ſt a Form to future dayes:</l>
            <l>If witneſs may be lawfull, then</l>
            <l>I'le ſweare 't ſhall fear no Vote of men;</l>
            <l>But to thy ever-ſhining Glory,</l>
            <l>The times to come ſhall hug thy Story.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. BOURNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="from John Hall" type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my much honoured Friend, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, on his Hiſtory of</hi> Amandus <hi>and</hi> Sophronia. In a Dialogue, between <hi>Menander</hi> and <hi>Muſeus.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Menan.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>MUſeus,</hi> how doſt brook to be</l>
               <l>Thus rival'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſ.</speaker>
               <l>Fate doth find I ſee</l>
               <l>'Tis fit, all Glory ſhould not die</l>
               <l>Entail'd unto our memorie,</l>
               <l>Where's thy <hi>Aglaia?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>Where is laid</l>
               <l>Thy much renowned <hi>Seſtian</hi> Maid?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſ.</speaker>
               <l>Beneath a myrtle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>So is mine</l>
               <l>Pratling, with Queen <hi>Proſerpine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mine laughs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſ.</speaker>
               <l>Mine weeps.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>Mine joyes to find</l>
               <l>Another of as rich a mind.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Muſ.</speaker>
               <l>But <hi>Venus</hi> Prieſteſſe is in grief,</l>
               <l>She now no longer ſhall be Chief,</l>
               <l>But with <hi>Leander</hi> muſt give way</l>
               <l>T' <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Sophronia.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>JOHN HALL</hi> Collegij Regnalis <hi>Canta.</hi> in Artibus Magiſtro.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="from Anthony Davenport" type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:4"/>
            <head>In Authorem Amiciſſimum ſuum, Encomiaſticon.</head>
            <l>LAdies, you that hug the Quill</l>
            <l>Of Renowned <hi>Aſtrophil</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Here, behold a ſecond Birth,</l>
            <l>Taſting of <hi>Sydnean</hi> worth.</l>
            <l>For <hi>Pyrocles,</hi> here, you may</l>
            <l>Find an <hi>Amandus,</hi> every way</l>
            <l>His Rivall; in <hi>Clodomer</hi> view</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Baſilius,</hi> and his humour too:</l>
            <l>This is ſo like in every lim</l>
            <l>To <hi>Sydney,</hi> that 'twas got by him</l>
            <l>I' de ſweare, but I ſhould injure then</l>
            <l>One of our nobleſt <hi>Shepherds</hi> Pen.</l>
            <l>See how the Learned ſhades do meet,</l>
            <l>And like Aeriall ſhadowes fleet,</l>
            <l>More in number then were ſpide</l>
            <l>To flock 'bout the <hi>Dulichian</hi> Guide.</l>
            <l>The firſt, <hi>Muſeus,</hi> then <hi>Catullus,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then <hi>Naſo, Flaccus,</hi> and <hi>Tibullus;</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:5"/>
            <l> Then <hi>Petrach, Sydney,</hi> none can move</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Shakeſpeare</hi> out of <hi>Adonis</hi> Grove,</l>
            <l>There ſullenly he ſits; but theſe</l>
            <l>Admire thy novell Rhapſodies.</l>
            <l>Dear Friend, which ever ſhall ſubſiſt,</l>
            <l>Spight of <hi>Oblivion's</hi> hiding-miſt.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>ANTHONY DAVENPORT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66275:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE LOVES OF</hi> AMANDVS <hi>AND</hi> SOPHRONIA.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>The Firſt Book.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Embaſſadours (from divers parts of</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope) <hi>arrive at</hi> Verona, <hi>the occaſion thereof.</hi> Rhoxenor <hi>courts</hi> Sophronia. <hi>Her Reply. He reſolves her Ruine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nciently there Reigned a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Potent King over the Kingdom of <hi>Lombardie,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Clodomer,</hi> who, by his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66275:6"/> Queen <hi>(Lucinda)</hi> had one only Son, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> a Prince of Exquiſite Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who, as he attained yeares, became Splendidly Eminent, for his Inclination to, and his unparralleld Induſtry in, the Study of the Sciences; to which, (that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be wanting, to make him more then a meere mortal) his Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment commanded an expectation of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick Magnanimitie, and Magnanimous Majeſtie, to the envy of neighbouring Kings, and to the ineffable joy of his Princely Parents.</p>
                  <p>Comming unto yeares of maturitie (ſo that now without prejudice to Truth he might write himſelfe, <hi>Man)</hi> he ſeemed, ſome golden Casket repleat with Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds: the eyes of all men were fixed on him, as ordained by Heaven, for a Super-excellent Mirrour, whoſe very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection ſhould dim the Splendor of all Former, and Future Kings: Their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, labouring with an ardent deſire, to ſee their young Prince fettered, in the pleaſing Bands of Matrimony, the main <hi>Remora</hi> (in their apprehenſions) being his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66275:6"/> high Deſcent, and innate Worth, which ſeated him on ſo proud a Pinacle, that nothing, ſave a continuance in his ſingle Capacitie, could preſerve his Splendor unſullied, and his Glory un-eclipſed, they could have been content, that their Phoenix ſhould have made himſelfe his owne Mate, and his owne Heire, ſave that they were ſenſible, another <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> would not ſpring out of his aſhes.</p>
                  <p>But what Mortalitie had ever yet a durable exiſtence of it ſelfe? What more vertuous Prince then <hi>Nero,</hi> the firſt five yeares? The Father of us all, retained his priſtine purity for ſome houres in the Garden. The Effigie of <hi>Byancha,</hi> Daughter to the King of <hi>Hungarie:</hi> The Reſemblance of <hi>Leonora,</hi> Heire apparant to the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> and the lively Portraicture of <hi>Dulciana,</hi> (whoſe living ſubſtance was courted by the moſt famous Princes of <hi>Europe)</hi> Daughter to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of <hi>Almaine,</hi> brought by ſeverall Embaſſadours, ſent from the aforeſaid Kings, all uſing their utmoſt Oratory to winne <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> aſſent, in the behalfe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66275:7"/> their ſeverall Maſters, bringing with them (as Advocates) many rich preſents, were fruſtrated of their hopes, by his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory negation, to their exceeding grief and aſtoniſhment,</p>
                  <p>Now, if you demand the reaſon of this ſtrange averſeneſſe in <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> I ſhall tell you, that Luſt, outragious, injurious, deſtructive Luſt, was the impediment that hindered his compliance, which had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch ſure hold on his heart, that it was impoſſible for the hand of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to diſlocate the Uſurper, without pulling the panting lump from its ſtrings; nor was <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> able (though he inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fagitably endeavoured it) to conjure down this Fiend, that his owne indiſcreet paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had raiſed, ſo that he was every way ſurrounded with inevitable dangers, <hi>Scylla</hi> on the right hand, and <hi>Charibdis</hi> on the left; <hi>Aetna</hi> on the left hand, and <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> on the right; (with <hi>Maedea)</hi> he ſaw, and knew the horrour of his Crime, and yet (thruſt forward by unavoydable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny) he could not but proceed in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petration thereof.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66275:7"/>
                  <p> And that, though he knew this would occaſion his owne loſſe of former Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; his Royal Parents Rage and Grief; <hi>Amandus</hi> (once his <hi>alter idem,</hi> having been bred up with him from his Cradle, now upon his returne from caſtigating the <hi>Girpides,</hi> the Souldiers unanimouſly and cordially affecting him) his aſſured hate and vengeance, beſides the uglineſſe of the Act, in wronging ſo noble a friend, together with the hazard of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Gentries, and Peoples revolt; yet to enjoy (indeed force) <hi>Sophronia</hi> (alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy affianced to <hi>Amandus)</hi> he is content to loſe all, and to make himſelfe wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the fruition of that (which if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) is (in truth) the worſt of miſerie.</p>
                  <p>Long (during <hi>Amandus</hi> abſence) hee converſed with the chaſt <hi>Sophronia</hi> (whom the King for <hi>Amandus</hi> ſake had appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a reſidence neare his owne lodgings) rather like a Brother then a Lover. [So the Wolfe, and the Lamb, converſe in amity, till maturitie divulge how diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently Nature hath allotted them] Love, (if I may call it Love) by degrees (like
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66275:8"/> ſupplanting Ivie) wound about his heart, till at laſt it maſtered his Senſes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topping and triumphing over all his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; ſo that [after many apparant ſignes of his inward Ardour, more then ever <hi>Naſo</hi> preſcribed in his <hi>Art of Love,</hi> which <hi>Sophronia</hi> did, but would not ſeeme to apprehend] he burſt out into a plaine lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, thus uttering his deſires.</p>
                  <p>Madam,</p>
                  <p>I <hi>Have endeavoured (with a more then maſculine reſolve) to ſuppreſſe thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and to extinguiſh thoſe flames, which have a long time hover'd about my heart, but find it beyond my force, not to write, when Nature her ſelfe dictates.</hi> (Lady) <hi>I love you, love you above Heaven, or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour (both which [in all probabilities] I am like to forfeit for your ſake) I am not ignorant of your affiancing to</hi> Amandus, <hi>but (deare Miſtreſſe) conſider my Birth with his Fortunes, and my Eſtate with his Wealth, and you cannot (ſure) relinquiſh the gold, and deſire the braſſe; this heavenly beauty was not ordained for leſſe then a Throne,</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66275:8"/> 
                     <hi>and it were an injury to Divinity it ſelfe, to have theſe Temples adorned, with ought ſave a Diadem; it is in you (excellent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe) to make</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>more than man, or to uncreate him, (which alone your deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all can doe) and to precipitate him, from an Heaven of content and happineſſe, to an Hell of diſtraction and miſery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You may imagine, how this unlook'd for narration, amazed poore <hi>Sophronia,</hi> (a Lady excellently vertuous) and whoſe heart was as immoveably fixed on <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus,</hi> as ever the <hi>Seſtian Heros</hi> on her adventurous <hi>Leander,</hi> or the unfortunate <hi>Thysbes,</hi> on her hapleſſe <hi>Pyramus,</hi> whoſe blood gave the firſt tincture to the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, her cheeks dyed in more perfect Purple, then Monarchs put on when they mourne, ſhe returned him this anſwer:</p>
                  <p>Sir,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your language (which I wiſh I had been deafe to) gives me cauſe to ſuſpect, that ſome ſaucy Devil (to be thought an Angel of light) hath cheated</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>of his form; for ſure, Prince</hi> Rhoxenor <hi>(I mean King</hi> Clodomers <hi>Son) whom Fame canonizeth,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66275:9"/> 
                     <hi>for the ſtore-houſe of Vertue, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of mankinde, cannot be ſuch a Traytor to his own fame, and his friends honour, or imagine</hi> Sophronia, <hi>ſo light of ſoule, as to prove falſe to her faith, to be the greateſt Princeſſe in the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus ſaid, (the vehemency of her expreſſion, well denoting the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of her mind) ſhe flung from him, in a (ſober) rage, and the Garden doore being open (for <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> the more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely to diſcover himſelfe, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited her into the privy Garden, adjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Pallace) ſhe forſook the Prince, and retired to her Chamber.</p>
                  <p>He, as much aſtoniſhed at her ſterne reply, as ſhe greived, for his dangerous ſolicitation, ſtood a while, like one Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ſtruck; you would have taken him (had your eyes viſited him in that agony) for ſome ſhap'd Statue, carved by ſome cunning <hi>Dedalus:</hi> but at length, his loſt ſenſes (like trewant Servants) returning to their obliged exerciſes, ſmiting his hand on his breaſt (quoth he) I perceive, I may ſooner catch a falling Star, or make
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66275:9"/> a bonefire in the Seas bottome, then win the favour of this icie peice; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (for the future) I ſhall (with <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fox) deſpiſe the fruition of that, which in affecting, I cannot attain; yet ſhall ſhe know, that Princes muſt of neceſſity, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther love affectionately, or hate deadly; and ſince my ſelfe muſt not enjoy her, I will ſo contrive, that <hi>Amandus</hi> ſhall not: having uttered this, in a great rage, he left the Garden, and departed towards the Pallace, in ſo moody a manner, that none of his Attendance, durſt ſpeake to him; and to thoſe Lords that ſaluted him, he returned no anſwer, to the exceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement of the Court, who wonder at (but cannot gueſſe) the cauſe of his change of cheare; the people whiſpering vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but nothing truly, according to the wildneſſe of their fancies.</p>
                  <p>Thus he, who not many months ſince, ſeemed to rivall that Prince of Planets, the Sunne, for tranſlucency, and clearneſſe, will now ſcarce ſerve for a Lunary in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes</hi> Spheare, <hi>So great is the folly, that commeth of Wiſdome, and ſo dreadfull is the</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66275:10"/> 
                     <hi>wickedneſſe, that ariſeth out of the aſhes of a dead vertue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Rhoxenor <hi>exceedingly perplexed,</hi> Cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brert <hi>diſcovers the cauſe of his dolour; his wicked counſell, he undertakes the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe about</hi> Sophronia.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O great was <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> anguiſh, conceived, for the late repulſe offered him by <hi>Sophronia,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated by his innate aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that his hopes were for ever buried in the Lathe of her chaſte Love to <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> that he ſcarce refrained to offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to his own Perſon; and though <hi>Cheribrert</hi> his creature (though his Fathers Counſellour) and to whom he had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to unbowelled himſelfe upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was importunately ſolicitous, to gain from him the leaſt part of that which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned his ſorrow; yet it ſeemed he had exchanged tongues with ſome Fiſh,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66275:10"/> no anſwer was returned to any of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: ſo that it was all one, as if he had entred into dialogue with a Statue, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a reſponſion, from the painted mouth of a Picture on the wall, to the great griefe of <hi>Clodimer,</hi> and <hi>Lucinda,</hi> who mourned for their Sonne as he were now to be inhumed, or were already ſleeping in a ſheet of Lead.</p>
                  <p>In this dolourous diſtracted condition, he abode the ſpace of eight dayes, eating little, and ſleeping leſſe, till one day (as he was toſſing himſelfe on his Couch) <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribrert,</hi> unawares entring in, and ſtanding a while at the door, to liſten if he could heare the Prince pronounce the leaſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, that might give him an hint of that which afflicted him, he heard him uſe theſe words to himſelfe;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ah</hi> Sophronia, <hi>thus thy unkindneſſe, will procure the certaine ruine of thy ſelfe, and me, and endanger the devaſtation of a flouriſhing Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> glad of this Intelligence, as if he had heard nothing, enters in, after his wonted manner, and (as his uſuall cuſtome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66275:11"/> was) beſought him, now at laſt to diſcover his greife; for (quoth he) be confident (Sir) of cure, if it be in the power of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Earth, or Hell to afford it: But find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſtill wedded to his wonted taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnity; (quoth he) my Lord, you are conſcious (I am ſure) of the knowledge I am famous for in Aſtrology; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving calculated your Nativity, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe uſed my Art to the utmoſt, I finde that you are in Love; <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> ſtarting from his Couch, at that word, ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his feet, (quoth he) but though (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) by thy Art, thou haſt found out the cauſe, it is not in the power of gods, or men to preſcribe the cure: My Lord (quoth <hi>Cheribrert)</hi> (having ever born a deadly hate to <hi>Amandus.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Trees, that will not bend, are as eaſily broken; tis at your diſcretion, though you cannot take in the Towne by Seige, to ſhake it to duſt, with your battery; by all that's ſacred, and the bright Genius of this place, I vow to ſacrifice ſoule and body to purchaſe your content, though your commands extended to the killing of my Father.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:66275:11"/>
                  <p> Quoth <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> and therewith fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a deep ſigh, grating his teeth) Take then the dreadful ſecret into thy boſome, I love <hi>Sophronia (Amandu's</hi> betrothed wife) but her Perſon I muſt never expect to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, which though I am content to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; yet ſuch is the rigour of my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that the damned endure not more unexpreſſable torments in hell, then I, when I but entertain a thought, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus,</hi> or any elſe, ſhall have the fruition of that Paradice, from entring into which, a Cherubin (with a flaming Sword) is my <hi>Remora;</hi> I would fain work the coy <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia,</hi> ſome deep diſgrace, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive, that <hi>Amandus</hi> may be made incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of her imbraces.</p>
                  <p>To this <hi>Cheribrert</hi> (laughing aloud) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd; And hath this ſleight buſineſſe (my Lord) occaſione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all this adoe, to the diſhonour of your ſelfe, the griefe of <hi>Clodomer,</hi> and <hi>Lucinda,</hi> and the generall diſcourſe, and deſtraction of the whole Realme? by the Soule of the world (my Lord) you have moſt indiſcreetly fool'd your ſelfe.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:66275:12"/>
                  <p> Why (quoth <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> doſt thou make ſo ſlight of it?</p>
                  <p>Yes, (quoth <hi>Cheribrert)</hi> for is it not in you, to diſpoſe of <hi>Sophronia,</hi> and <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> as you ſhall thinke fit? are they not your Subjects, and Servants, are not (or ought not) their lives and eſtates, to be at your appointment, as other your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Subjects, whoſe Heire aparent you are? Depute me (my Lord) for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of this buſineſſe, and if I act not like another <hi>Mercury,</hi> wittily, yet like ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saturne,</hi> malevolently, decapitate me, and fix this head on the cheife Gate of the City.</p>
                  <p>I ever (quoth <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> have found thee cordially fidelious, doe but doe as thou haſt indented, and expect what wealth, or honour thou canſt covet, while <hi>Clodomer</hi> lives, and when his death, puts the Diadem upon my head, to be my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favourite.</p>
                  <p>I (quoth <hi>Cheribrert)</hi> ſhall eſteem the fulfilling of your commands, rewards ſufficient. I joy that Fate hath found out away for me, to expreſſe the loyall duty
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66275:12"/> I owe to your Highneſſe.</p>
                  <p>And ſo for that time they departed one from another, the Prince to the Court, and <hi>Cheribrert</hi> to his own manſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Cheribrert <hi>(by the aide of</hi> Flavia, Sophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias <hi>Woman) betrayes</hi> Sophronia <hi>to the cenſure of the Law, the manner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Onderfull it is to conſider, how great an influence the interior parts of man, have on his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior; <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> had almoſt vext himſelfe to a <hi>Skelleton,</hi> but now [re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on <hi>Cheribrerts</hi> abillity, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of his wicked deſignes] his minde being calmed, his whole <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme</hi> reſumed its wonted vigour.</p>
                  <p>[So the vegitables of the earth, when the froſty hand of <hi>Hyems</hi> hath diſpoyled them of their verdant garments, remaine (for a time) as it were, ſapleſſe; but when <hi>Hyperion</hi> brings on the ſpring, they are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66275:13"/> againe adorned in their ſummer glory] <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> hath the ſame health (though not the ſame purity) he formerly enjoyed, to the generall rejoycing of all men.</p>
                  <p>But now was <hi>Cheribrert</hi> devizing how to expreſſe himſelfe a faithfull Servant, to his ignoble Maſter, ſometime he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves on this, but then another conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration proves it abortive: now he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth that, as the ſureſt, and moſt facile way; but cogitating how it may prove in the Cataſtrophe, he waveth it, as ſuggeſted by the Feinds to his owne ruine; at length he concluded on a way, moſt probable, for the effecting of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, which was this:</p>
                  <p>The vertuous <hi>Sophronio</hi> had an Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, whom ſhe peculiarly reflected on, named <hi>Flavia;</hi> her he had a long time endeavoured to winne to his laſcivious embraces, with all manner of rich gifts, and faire promiſes, but had ſtill failed in his hopes; the Virgins breaſt being Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proofe, againſt all the fiery aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of this Fiend; yet in caſe he could affect her honourably, in the way of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66275:13"/> ſhe denyed not, to meet his love with equall Fervour: By this Virgins means, he doubted not (though one would think he had cauſe enough to be diffident) to fulfill his engagement to <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> and attaine his propoſed ends.</p>
                  <p>With all ſpeed therefore he reſorts to <hi>Flavia,</hi> (who was hardly drawne to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company him, imagining he yet came to demand that which ſhe never meant to give) and having declared unto her his (ſeeming) noble intents (to make her his Wife, and ſharer with him, in all he could call his) ſhe look'd upon him with a more pleaſing aſpect then hitherto ſhe had done; her geſture proclaiming, ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded his intents, and with him would cheerfully accord to ſing Paeans to <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having aſſured her his reality, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny oaths and imprecations, calling the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Gods to witneſſe the Integrity of his heart (quoth he)</p>
                  <p>My deare, ſince now nothing wants, ſave ſome few ceremonious Formes, to make us one fleſh, Heaven forbid wee
<pb facs="tcp:66275:14"/> ſhould deny to accompliſh any thing one for another, not beyond our ability to performe. So it is, that the Prince <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> (upon thy life, weare the ſecret next thy heart) is deeply enamoured on thy Miſtreſſe, who he hath ſolicited in as quaint Oratory, as ever <hi>Demoſthenes, Quintilian,</hi> or <hi>Tully</hi> were maſters of, yet neither his words, preſents, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, have proved of force enough to thaw her froſty chaſtitie: Now, it is in thee, to gaine him the fruition of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and to make me (thy Husband) great in Riches and Honours; I know, ſhe permits none to have natures beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by her ſave thee; too morrow night therefore, the Prince <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> adorned with theſe very garments thou haſt on, ſhall ſlip into thy Miſtreſſe bed, which happineſſe, when he hath once attained, if he loſe the fruition of his bliſſe by Cowardice, let <hi>Cupid</hi> break his head with his Bow, or <hi>Venus</hi> ſtrangle him with her Ceſton.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Flavia,</hi> ſtood a while in a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> not knowing what anſwer to returne,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66275:14"/> yet at length <hi>(Oh the frailty of woman kind, who, if they reſiſt the aſſault the one way, are eaſily ſurpriſed by the other)</hi> ſhe conſented to act according to his preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſhe whoſe chaſtity could not be undermined by luſt, or gaine, had her fidelity blowne up by the hope of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugall Wealth, and matrimoniall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
                  <p>Night now drew her Curtaine o're the World, and the chaſte <hi>Sophronia</hi> preparing for Bed, was enforced to uſe the ayde of ſome other Handmaid, <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi> (by <hi>Cheribrerts</hi> advice) keeping out of the way on purpoſe. <hi>Sophronia</hi> entring her Bed, ſeemed like Bow-arm'd <hi>Diana,</hi> ſtripping her ſelfe of her ornaments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to bath her Deifide body in ſome Chriſtall Fountaine, ſhe was (indeed) an Adornment to that which Adorned her; the Arts, which other Ladies uſe to adde to the Luſtre of their Beauties, would have dimmed her natural exquiſite Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: So great were her outward Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that, not <hi>Paetrarch,</hi> or <hi>Sydney,</hi> (were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66275:15"/> they alive) could find pertinent Elocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſutable to her Eulogie: So glorious were her inward endowments, that none ſave <hi>Apollo</hi> himſelf, or rather the tongue of ſome <hi>Cherub,</hi> can ſpeak them.</p>
                  <p>By this time pernicious <hi>Cheribrert</hi> had ſo dealt with a ſervant of his (no worſe Officer then the Groome of his Stable) whom he had decked (with the Jay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by <hi>Aeſop)</hi> in <hi>Flavia's</hi> Plumes, and with faire words, and rich promiſes, had ſo fortified his courage, that he reſolutely entred <hi>Sophronia's</hi> Chamber, (having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the key of the door from <hi>Flavia,</hi> in whom <hi>Sophronia</hi> repoſed ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that ſhe made her [as it were] the Guardianeſſe of her perſon) the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low being entred, found the Excellent La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy faſt aſleep (ſo fatall was her chance, and ſo direfull her deſtiny) rejoycing thereat, he beckned to <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> and <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribret</hi> (who ſtood at the ſtaire-foot) to come up, who did ſo, and with eaſie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion planted themſelves in a corner of the roome, behind the Arras, while the fellow went to bed; no ſooner in, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66275:15"/> 
                     <hi>Cheribrert</hi> and the Prince left their ſtation, and with loud cries, awaked the Chaſt Lady, who, amazed at the ſuddenneſſe of the thing, and wondring to behold <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribrert,</hi> and <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> by her beds ſide, alſo perceiving the doore of her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber wide open, but looking upon the ſlave that had adventured into her bed, and finding him not to be <hi>Flavia,</hi> with a lowd ſhreitch ſhe leaped out of the bed, and was entertained by the Prince, into his Armes, though not with a Lovers embraces</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O horrour (quoth</hi> Cheribrert) <hi>calling his man by his name) what ſawcie Fiend prompted thee to this villanie, to the never to be obliterated infamy of our Noble Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> Amandus, <hi>the deep diſgrace of all Ladies in this Kingdome; Heaven knowes how often ſhe hath ſated her ſalt luſt with this ſtallion, and therewithall, he thruſt a poniard to the fellowes heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou mayſt report it in the other World (quoth he) but never in this, that thou haſt had to doe with ſo beauteous a Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:66275:16"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>O Heaven (quoth Rhoxener) is this your love to</hi> Amandus <hi>(Lady) what woman may be truſted?</hi> We give our Soules to the Devil for a little Letchery, and a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man makes the Contract. <hi>Was this the occaſion I appeared ſo deſpicable in your eies, an horſe-heel-rubber your Paramour; by all the Gods, I tremble to thinke of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate dotage, and had not mine eyes been witneſſes of this horrour, I ſhould not have credited the Narration, had</hi> Apollo <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced it: But be your ſinne to your ſelf, your Letcher hath paid for his wharfage al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and is now entring into</hi> Charons <hi>boat: For your part (though your life bee forfeit by the Law) both triall, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſhall be adjourned, till</hi> Amandus <hi>have reſigned his Wreath at the feet of Fame, and ſhall have opportune leaſure to hear the Hiſtory of his own ſhame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The betrayed <hi>Sophronia,</hi> was ſo vaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized to terrour, that ſhe could not ſpeak one word, but ſwouned away, ſo that they were forced to ſhew her ſome ſmall curteſie againſt their wils, (ſuch as the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66275:16"/> Spaniſh Inquiſitors extend to thoſe they put to the Rack, give them ſome reſpite to recover their limbs anew, and more fiercely to torment them) and to put her into her bed, for her recovery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> uncaſing his dead Hireling, left him on the floore, throwing his own habit (which he ware under his womans weed) over him, and putting <hi>Flavia's</hi> gowne under his cloake, departed, with <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> to the Pallace, of whom, read more in the next Chapter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Sophronia <hi>(by the Kings command) carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Priſoner to</hi> Caſtle Angellina: <hi>Her Deportment there.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Prince, having finiſhed this unprincely work (by the help of his wretched Inſtrument, <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> to whom he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed great rewards for this ſervice) reſorts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66275:17"/> to the King his Father, to whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the debauchery of <hi>Sophronia, Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribrert</hi> ſeconding the ſame, and adding, that he was ſo exaſperated, and vaſſaliz'd to paſſion at the knowledge thereof, that he had juſtly (though unadviſedly) ſlain his own Servant (her Paramour) with his poniard. <hi>Clodomer</hi> (who little ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the treacherie of <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> and <hi>Cheribrert)</hi> after ſome diſpute with thoſe about him, concluded to commit her priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to <hi>Caſtle Angellina,</hi> there to remain, till time ſhould further their intents for her triall, and puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Unfortunate <hi>Sophronia</hi> was hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to her gadding Senſes, when the Captain of the Guard (furniſhed with plenary power to apprehend, and ſeclude her perſon) came to convey her to the place appointed; to whoſe power, ſhee willingly ſubmitted, like ſome innocent Lamb, invironed by a crew of ravenous Wolves, her Innocence, was her Shield; her Puritie, her Defence; her Chaſtity, her Solace; and her Sanctity, her San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66275:17"/>
                  <p> Being come to the Caſtle, (or rather Casket, appointed to retaine ſo ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Jewell) ſhe was received by the Keeper thereof, whoſe wife, an old Crone, more deformed of mind, then body, took upon her to provide for her, lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her in a chamber on the North-ſide of the Caſtle, ſo near the Sea, that ſometimes <hi>Neptune</hi> watered the very windows there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, where, taking a coale from the hearth, ſhe wrote theſe verſes on the wall.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ye faire</hi> Nereides, <hi>who love to ſweep</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(In ſedgy Chariots drawn) the foaming deep;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou chaſt</hi> Actea, <hi>and</hi> Uronea <hi>ſage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cymodoce, <hi>that</hi> Neptune <hi>canſt aſſwage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Themiſte, Nemertea, Spio, <hi>all</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yee ſeed of</hi> Doris, <hi>hearken to my call.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I am</hi> Sophronia, <hi>by baſe luſt betraid</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By Prince</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>in a dungeon laid:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chant you my name aloud in</hi> Thetis <hi>Court,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And wealthy</hi> Rhea, <hi>ſhe wil thank you for't;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or elſe convey the Story of my woe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To my</hi> Amandus <hi>(oh) did he but know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Innocence occaſions me this ill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Clodomer, <hi>and</hi> Rhoxenor <hi>both, hee'd kill;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:66275:18"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>But do not as I wiſh, I ſpeak in paſsion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Clodomer <hi>is the Father of my Nation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Son our Hope and Prop, here let me die;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet if I hap to have an Obſequie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This Epitaph inſculpe upon my Tomb.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Here by the deſtinies injurious doome</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hapleſs</hi> Sophronia <hi>lies, kild in her prime</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For to be truly chaſte was all her crime.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>After ſhe had finiſhed theſe Verſes, ſhe ſate her down, reſolved to beare patiently whatſoever the will of Heaven ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, with as little repining, as her cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſufferance, and womaniſh frailty would permit; where for a while I muſt leave her, for it is high time we viſited <hi>Amandus,</hi> and accompanied him into his own Countrey.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:66275:18"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Amandus <hi>(having conquered the</hi> Girpids) <hi>returnes Victorious to</hi> Verona. <hi>His So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Entertainment.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hile <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> and <hi>Cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brert</hi> were applauding their fortunate ſucceſſe in the late buſineſſe, mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt <hi>Sophronia; Rhoxenor</hi> pleaſing himſelfe with the thought of <hi>Sophronia's</hi> dolour, and <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribrert</hi> promiſing himſelfe that this would prove the <hi>praeludium</hi> to <hi>Amandus</hi> down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall, knowing how ſtrongly he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his Miſtreſſe Chaſtity. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> (having approved himſelfe the Maſter of <hi>Mavors,</hi> and taught the <hi>Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pids,</hi> who, being tributary to the <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards,</hi> had rebelled, that the <hi>Lombards</hi> merited the Supremacie, excelling them both in Wiſedome, and Valour) with his chief Captaines, <hi>Venantius, Palladius, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante,</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66275:19"/> and others (after 11 months abſence) returned towards his owne Countrey, with many Priſoners, and rich Spoile, the people ſtrowing Flowers, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting him with Gifts all the way, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him their <hi>PRESERVER,</hi> his <hi>COUNTRIES CHAMPION,</hi> and the <hi>WARS GLORY;</hi> all which, he accepted with ſuch a Deportment, as neither manifeſted he was proud of their Applauſe, or ſcorned their Kindneſſe.</p>
                  <p>In this manner, he march'd towards <hi>Verona,</hi> not far from whence, the King <hi>Clodomer,</hi> Queen <hi>Lucinda,</hi> Prince <hi>Rhoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Cheribrert,</hi> and all of the Councell, with infinite numbers of the Gentry on Horſe-back, and an innumerable number of the Vulgar on foot, came out to meet him, in this manner.</p>
                  <p>Firſt came the King <hi>Clodomer,</hi> wrapt in Ermins skins, on his head, the Diadem of <hi>Lombardie,</hi> on a ſtately Gennet, trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with Gold, a Canopy of <hi>Tyrian</hi> Silk, with Gold Fringe, borne above his Head, by foure Noble men of eſpeciall note, on each ſide of him (for he was a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66275:19"/> lover of learning, and learned men) a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Biſhop, the one named <hi>Otho,</hi> the other <hi>Othello,</hi> in their pontificall Attire, mounted on red Horſes (to ſignifie, that by them the Almighty power diſpenſeth his Judgements and mercies.)</p>
                  <p>Then followed all the Nobillity of that Kingdome (according to their ſeverall Gradations) cloathed and mounted like petty Princes, as you ſee in a ſharp win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter night, when the leſſer Luminaries of Heaven are congregated [as if met in counſell, to contrive the ruine of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lady <hi>Phoebe]</hi> one farre exceedeth another in luſter; ſo was it amongſt this Noble train, all ſtrove for precedency, ſo that there could not be a parity: after theſe, came five Troops of Celeſtiall Choriſters on foot, habited in black, with Palms in their hands, ſinging Paeans all the way, and playing on ſeverall ſorts of Inſtruments, to which their tuneable voyces, ſo admirably accented, that ſome would needs conceit, they were now taking their journey to <hi>Elizium,</hi> with their King and his Councell.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:66275:20"/>
                  <p> After theſe, came the Prince <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> with <hi>Cheribrert</hi> and two more, all clad (like himſelfe) in black, their Horſes of the ſame colour, to the exceeding wonder of all men.</p>
                  <p>After whom, came the Queen <hi>Lucinda,</hi> mounted on an Unicorn (a woman though in yeares, of exceeding comlineſſe, tall of ſtature, majeſtick of countenance, having the work <hi>Queen,</hi> written in her forehead) with all her traine of Ladies following her, deck'd in all the ſpoiles of nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Like ſo many Conſtellations, convened in the upper Region of the Air, their contracted luſter forced the Sunne (that greedily gazed upon them, to confeſſe, that his own Climine was rivalled by the meaneſt there) to muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle his glorious head in a Cloud, ſo that</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinda, <hi>attended by theſe, ſeemed another</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tona, <hi>glyding ore the</hi> Spartane Tageytus, <hi>with all her train of Nymphs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus,</hi> with <hi>Pallante, Venantius, Palladius,</hi> and the chiefeſt of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, drawing neare the King, deſerted their Horſes, and ſtanding on foot, were honoured with <hi>Clodomers</hi> hand, which they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66275:20"/> affectionately laid their lips to; the two Church-men, <hi>Otho,</hi> and <hi>Othello,</hi> congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating <hi>Amandus</hi> arrivall, briefly, but pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</p>
                  <p>Then came the Prince <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> who ſalluted <hi>Amandus</hi> at ſo great diſtance, as (conſidering their affectionate intimacie formerly, beyond that of <hi>Pylades,</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> or <hi>Damon,</hi> and <hi>Pythias)</hi> much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed him; <hi>Cheribrert</hi> ſeemed ſo much raviſhed with joy, that the Organs of his ſpeech, were quite damn'd up, yet he made many humble and obſequious congees. <hi>Amandus</hi> found it no fit time, now, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into dialogue with <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the cauſe, that had ſo incredibly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged him, and therefore he refrained himſelfe, and counterfeited a mirthfull cheare, and the rather (for that the Prince having joyned himſelfe to his Father) ſeeing <hi>Lucinda</hi> came on, with all her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious traine, (in the principall ranke of whom, he aſſuredly expected to have bleſt his eyes, with the ſight of his divine Lady <hi>Sophronia)</hi> who likewiſe offered <hi>Amandus,</hi> and his aſſociate Friends, the ſame honour
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66275:21"/> that <hi>Clodomer</hi> before had done, which they ſubmiſſively accepted.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Amandus</hi> (none blame him for it) was in great anxiety of mind (as the odd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his geſture well denoted) at the ſtrange carriage of things, he perceived the King beheld him, but with halfe a face, ſeeming more to reflect upon his Officers <hi>(Venantius,</hi> and <hi>Palladius)</hi> then himſelfe; then, the Prince to meet him (at ſuch a time) in ſwarthy weeds, ſalluting him at more diſtance, then a country Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would view the Lyons at firſt time; and what was more horrible then Hell, not to have the ſight of <hi>Saphronia</hi> his ſoules life (whom he had left to <hi>Clodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> tuition, and protection) theſe ſeverall ill boading Omens: his jealous Fancy contracted into one ominous apparancy, which prompted him to prognoſticate ſome ſtrange Revolution had happened during his non-reſidency from <hi>Verona,</hi> yet ſuch was the noble temper of his ſoule, ſo great his Magnanimitie [imboldned by his Innocency] that hereſolved, not ſo much as tacitely to repine, but to waite
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66275:21"/> patiently, and (to humane veiw) content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, till time ſhould make a diſcovery, to the clearing of all doubts, and ſo fortified with this (truly heroick) reſolution, he ſet forward to the City.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Venantius, <hi>and</hi> Palladius, <hi>having bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an Engliſh Curtezan, &amp;c. are very Scurvily handled.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW for that the Reader will have enough of dolourous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ere the Hiſtory be brought to a period; it will not be amiſſe, if I recite one pleaſant paſſage, that happened to the two Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels, <hi>Venantius,</hi> and <hi>Palladius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Girpids</hi> thus ſubdued, by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of heaven, upon <hi>Amandus</hi> proweſſe, it was thought fit, no longer to keep the Army in pay (the maintenance of which, muſt needs prove an intollerable burthen to the Subject, eſpecially the Kingdome
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66275:22"/> not needing a viſible force) and therefore <hi>Clodomer</hi> having beſtowed great gratuities, and rich gifts (befitting his own magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and their merits) upon the ſeverall Commanders of the Army; with a largis to be diſtributed amongſt the common Souldiers, commanded them Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be disbanded, with a Proclamation of thanks, for their good ſervice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venantius, Palladius, Paradine,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelmus,</hi> the four principall Commanders under <hi>Amandus</hi> (I mention not <hi>Pallante,</hi> for he kept cloſe to the Generall, entirely loving, and entirely beloved of him) theſe Diſciples of <hi>Mars,</hi> who ſubſiſted by blood and ſweat, having now no further em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, in this Kingdome, reſolved to put themſelves, under the governance of the Duke <hi>Medina,</hi> Generall of a potent <hi>(Spaniſh)</hi> Army, for the invaſion of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>France,</hi> but ere they left <hi>Verona,</hi> they ſwore to make tryall, what Wine and Women the City afforded.</p>
                  <p>Being much of the mind of too many Martialliſts, managing the Army of the late King of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe vinall and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66275:22"/> venereall appetites have ruined the glory of all former and future Princes.</p>
                  <p>In order to this reſolution, they reſort to the ſigne of the Goddeſſe <hi>Venus,</hi> ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate on the eaſt ſide of the City, (it ſeemes, that Peſt houſes, and Bawdy houſes there, have equall appointment) a Tavern, kept by one <hi>Antonio Ronſardo,</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> who had to wife an <hi>Engliſh</hi> woman (a Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado from her firſt Mate, of comely fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) named <hi>Mariana</hi> (one, who when in <hi>England,</hi> was more afraid of a Shrove-tueſdayes Battery, then a guilty Wretch to view the face of an angry Judge) here being arrived, they were ſoon conducted into a tipling Tenement, where they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to drink like Dutch men, <hi>Clodomers, Lucindas, Rhoxenors,</hi> and <hi>Amandus</hi> healths were deeply cellebrated, and now being well heated with Wine, they knockd for <hi>Mariana</hi> the Miſtreſſe of the houſe, who came ſimpring into their company, like ſome nice Siſter of the new edition; and yet ere ſhe parted, received her <hi>Sallary,</hi> to make <hi>the Beaſt with two backs,</hi> with one and tother that night.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66275:23"/>
                  <p> Having received her Coin, <hi>viz.</hi> forty Crownes, ſhe left them to their mirth, who began to roar and ſing, no Engliſh Royſter beyond them; <hi>Venantius</hi> (as well as his new conceived hyccup would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) began to ſing this Catch:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let the Campe ſtay,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>and the Knapſack-bearers want their pay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>till to morrow;</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We all are agreed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>that</hi> Bachus <hi>ſhall bleed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>till drinking hath drowned our ſorrow.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What gaind</hi> Phillips <hi>Son, ſuch Conqueſt and Fame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And great</hi> Julius Caeſar <hi>ſo glorious a Name,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But tipling in Triumph,</hi> ſans <hi>limit or aime.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Pewh (quoth <hi>Palladius)</hi> there is no mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody in theſe Madrigals, no Songs pleaſe me, ſave thoſe that are dedicated at leaſt by a <hi>Cupid;</hi> heare mine, and with that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſing this.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66275:23"/>
                     <head>Song.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Why ſo coy and nice dear Lady,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pray you, why ſo nice?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You long to make your Lord a Daddy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is kiſsing then a vice,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>pray you, why ſo nice</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Why thoſe Pearles fetcht from the Ocean</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And thoſe Gems of price?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You know we men have heat and motian.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Theſe muſt needs entice</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>maugre all advice.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Why this</hi> Tyre <hi>with care contorted,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Why this</hi> Silk-worms <hi>toile,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And why theſe haires curiouſly ſorted</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bedew'd with ſacred Oyle</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ſave our bloods to boyle?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If Reſolution arme your heart</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis horrid Tyranny,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For to tranſluce us with Loves Dart</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And yet no cure apply</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>you are our mallady.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:66275:24"/>
                  <p> By this time they had ſufficiently fud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelves; the vapourous ſteam of both Ellements, I mean, the fumoſity of Wine, and the reaking ſent of that <hi>Indian</hi> Weed, now ſo common in uſe, began to foment a civill war in their crazed nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, to the infinite prejudice of their fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble braines, who now no longer able to ſtand upon their guard, yeilded themſelves captive, to the diſpoſall of their merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Conquerours; <hi>Paradine</hi> and <hi>Anſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> (the onely moderate men of the four) made a ſhift to grope the way to their lodgings, but <hi>Venantius</hi> and <hi>Palladius,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to give their money for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, although they were very diffident of ſome imbecillity already ſeized on their neather nerves.</p>
                  <p>Well, it now grew late, <hi>Mariana</hi> comes up to give them notice, that it was high time, to betake them to their reſt.</p>
                  <p>Sweet beauty (quoth <hi>Venantius)</hi> we ſhall not tantalize long, in expectation of your ſociety.</p>
                  <p>Doe you doubt me (quoth <hi>Mariana)</hi> be confident, I will be better than my word
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66275:24"/> to you; and ſo departed. They imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by the word <hi>Better,</hi> ſhe intimated, that ſhe would be with them ſooner then perhaps they thought, not imagining what after happened, and doubting nothing, went to bed together.</p>
                  <p>Now you muſt underſtand, that <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> perceiving <hi>Venantius</hi> and <hi>Palladius,</hi> to be Commanders of the Army under <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> (by whoſe Proclamation, it was death for any Officer, or Souldier, to ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licit another mans wife) and well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they durſt not attempt any thing afterward, ſhould ſhe uſe them for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent never ſo courſely, had reſolved to receive their money, but not to yeeld them the Commodity they bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for; and therefore had told them, that though her husband <hi>Ronſardo</hi> was out of town, yet there were ſo many Lodgers in the houſe, (who took ſtrict notice of her actions) that ſhe could by no means wait upon them in their own Chamber; yet (ſaid ſhe) if you dare run a little ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, for the thing you ſeem ſo to affect, all my Lodgers being in bed, the lodging
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66275:25"/> where you are to reſt to night, ſtands juſt over my Chamber, where is a Trap-door, of which I have the key; and when I perceive all quiet, will ſteale up, and open it my ſelfe (but take heed you preſerve no Candlle unextinguiſht) deſcending with you into mine own Chamber, where you may enjoy your wiſhes till morning.</p>
                  <p>This they were ſo fooliſh to beleeve, and waited her approach accordingly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venantius</hi> was the better Servant to <hi>Venus</hi> of the two, and therefore he infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced himſelfe to watchfullneſſe, but <hi>Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> (having drank hard) was no ſooner in bed, but he fell faſt aſleep, when not long after, up comes <hi>Mariana</hi> in the darke and finding no Candle in the Chamber.</p>
                  <p>Oh (quoth ſhe) this is well done, to put out the light: (quoth <hi>Venantius)</hi> although I could have wiſh'd a veiw of that ground I am to till, yet (for your ſake Lady) I am content to act all things <hi>in tenebris:</hi> come (quoth ſhe) all things are prepared below, there we may enjoy the reflection of a Taper without fear, which that we might doe, I have on purpoſe planted
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66275:25"/> one, in a darke lanthorne under the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  <p>Excellent creature (quoth <hi>Venantius)</hi> this ſhall for ever bind me to thee, body, and ſoul, let us deſcend: then perceiving <hi>Palladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſnoring by him, he endeavoured to rowz him, with puſhing, and pinching, and at laſt, with much adoe, did ſo.</p>
                  <p>You are a ſure card (quoth <hi>Mariana)</hi> I perceive, and in a fit capacity to cut capers.</p>
                  <p>Hang him dullard (quoth <hi>Venantius)</hi> let him ene ſnore till morning, I'le war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you (Lady) you will find enough of me.</p>
                  <p>By no meanes (quoth <hi>Mariana)</hi> for ſo we may be betraid; the Gentleman may perhaps wake, and finding himſelf alone, make a clamour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Palladius,</hi> half drunk, half ſober, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſleeping and waking, leaping out of the bed, would needs be the firſt that deſcended, which he did, departing ſo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently (as <hi>Venantius</hi> imagined) down the ſtayres, that he much marveiled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at.</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:66275:26"/>
                  <p> (Quoth he) ſure <hi>Palladius</hi> is acquainted with thoſe ſteps, and is not ſo drunke as I thought him to be.</p>
                  <p>May be ſo (quoth <hi>Mariana)</hi> now (Sir) take your progreſſe, I muſt goe laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of locking the doore, that nothing may be diſcerned in the morning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venantius,</hi> haſtily putting one of his feet forward to find a ſtaire, was cheated of his expectation, and violently preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated into a Jakes, adjacent to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhoare, where he found <hi>Palladius</hi> ſwearing and curſing, as he were mad.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mariana</hi> having lodged her Lovers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted (laughing) to her bed.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Venantius</hi> and <hi>Palladius</hi> were in a very ſtinking condition, and almoſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focated with the norſome ſteame, evapou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from that heap of dung with which they were invironed, almoſt up to the chins, ſo that the feare they were in, quite expelled their drunkenneſſe, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan now to cogitate how they might find delivery out of that dirty labyrinth, which with much adoe they attained, wandring ſo long till at laſt they came to the head
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66275:26"/> of a clear river, where they beſtowed ſome time to cleanſe themſelvs, and then joyned noddles, to conſider which way to take (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as they were.) But that which was the greateſt coraſive to their minds, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it impoſſible to recover any dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Mariana,</hi> or to plague her for their puniſhment; and therfore reſolving to make the beſt of a bad matter, they ſet forward very fairely towards <hi>Paradines</hi> lodging, of whom (after ſome diſpute) they gained admittance, where I leave them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:66275:27"/>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE LOVES OF</hi> SOPHRONIA <hi>AND</hi> AMANDVS <hi>The Second Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Great Revelling, and a Maſque at Court, its Preſentation:</hi> Amandus, <hi>in great ſorrow for his Miſtreſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rrived at <hi>Verona, Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> gave thankes to the people for their forward zeal, who with loud Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, (ſo that the Earth rang againe) pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Heavens to ſhowre downe their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66275:27"/> choiſeſt bleſſings upon him, departed to their homes.</p>
                  <p>This popular Applauſe, as it no whit contented <hi>Clodomer,</hi> ſo it put <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> and <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> into a cold ſweat: The King ſeemed highly to honour <hi>Amandus,</hi> whom the Nobles and Courtiers (who, as in a clock, are the leſſer wheeles, all pliable to the circular motion of the great one) generally imitated. <hi>Amandus</hi> was lodged the next Chamber to the King, who feaſted him with all variety of Cates, and curious Wines: The Earth, the Sea, and Aire, were all plundered of their eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Inhabitants, ſo that <hi>Lucullus</hi> (had he been there) would have repined at ſuch expenſive prodigality; ſo that for ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and luxurious fare, not <hi>Ninus</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; nor <hi>Cleopatra</hi> when ſhe feaſted <hi>Julius Caeſar;</hi> or <hi>Mark Anthony,</hi> was comparable. Without, was continually heard the ſound of Cornets, Shagbots, and Flutes: Within, the pleaſing melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Lutes, Vials, and Virginals; yet all this while no ſpeech of <hi>Sophronia.</hi> The Prince aſſociated <hi>Amandus,</hi> (tis true)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66275:28"/> but ſo, as if he had come on Embaſſage to denounce war, and not as his (ſometime) deare and boſome friend.</p>
                  <p>This, <hi>Amandus</hi> ſeemed to take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, knowing things could not long hang in ſuſpence: This was the twelfth day that <hi>Amandus</hi> had been a Courtier, when the King commanded <hi>Linus,</hi> his chief Poet, to deviſe a Maſque, ſutable to the preſent occaſion (to be preſented on the morrow, in the golden Theater) which <hi>Linus</hi> accordingly performed: And the King, with <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> on his Right hand, and <hi>Amandus</hi> on his Left, with all his Nobilitie at diſtance: And <hi>Lucinda,</hi> with all her Traine of Ladies at her feet, all things in readineſſe,</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>There was diſcovered</p>
                     <p>The Nymph <hi>Parthenope</hi> appearing, laid along on the brinke of a calme Sea, and there awaked by the noiſe of Trumpets and Drums; after her regreet (upon her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer repoſe, and preſent miſeries) <hi>Courage,</hi> and <hi>Fidelity,</hi> appeared to comfort her, who,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66275:28"/> having made a faire promiſe for the time to come, departed, and,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jupiter</hi> appeared from above, in a calm and Serene Skie, ſending her, for the more aſſurance of his word, his Meſſenger, <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> who deſcended from Heaven in a Cloud, bringing with him, <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Publick Tranquilitie,</hi> and joyning with <hi>Parthenope</hi> in a dance,</p>
                     <p>The Scene cloſed.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>This Device was exceedingly applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King, and all there preſent. <hi>Amandus</hi> (though he ſeemed attentive) could give but a very ſlender account of what he had ſeen, and heard, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of his eyes being reverſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and his thoughts wholy buſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Sophronia,</hi> ſo that (to him it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) he beheld a Matachin, and not a Maſque.</p>
                  <p>Yet though Poiſon, and Poniards, and all Inſtruments of ruine, were obvious to the eye of his mind, he cries, rarely plotted, and excellently preſented. <hi>Sol</hi> then giving place to <hi>Diana,</hi> put his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66275:29"/> to paſture, in <hi>Neptunes</hi> watry Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Kings Diſcourſe with</hi> Amandus <hi>in private. A Diſcovery of his Fathers wrongs. The Prince, and</hi> Cheribrert, <hi>juſtifie his Miſtreſſe lewdneſſe. His di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE King perceiving by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> countenance (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever imbelliſhed with feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſmiles) and his geſture, (however modellized into a pliant Garbe) that he was much troubled about ſomewhat, that he would be glad to heare, and yet w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to aske, carrying him with him one day alone into the Privy Garden, (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding that none whatſoever ſhould dare to interrupt him for an hour) he entred
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66275:29"/> with him into a pleaſant Arbor, ſituate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath a Mulbery tree, whoſe Fabrick was faſhioned of creeping Vines, intermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with bluſhing Roſes; ſitting him downe (willing <hi>Amandus</hi> to accompany him, ſince they were alone) he began thus to expreſſe himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>YOu cannot be ignorant (I am ſure) what a tender regard I have ever diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered towards you, from your infancy, even unto this preſent; I need not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how I found you at firſt, with what Indulgence I have nurtured you, and to what an height of honour my ſmiles have raiſed you; though I could ſay your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (I confeſſe a Peer of great Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, and of a vaſt Eſtate) left you, a deſolate Orphan (his prodigality having reduced him to ſuch penury, that I was forced to ſupport him out of my owne Revenew<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I could ſay, that I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you education, no whit inferiour to my Sonne <hi>Rhoxenor;</hi> and for your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity at preſent, I think I need not tel you;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66275:30"/> you cannot but find your ſelfe to move in the <hi>Apogaeum</hi> of Honour.</p>
                  <p>The King would have proceeded far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but <hi>Amandus</hi> (who could no longer keep ſilence) thus interrupted him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Royall Sir,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I Know not to what Port the winde of your <hi>praeludium</hi> may deſigne you, nor am I greatly timerous to ſtand the ſhock of that thunder this lightning portends: But I muſt tell you (Sir) it is not King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in you, to upraid him (whom I have hitherto thought) your vertuous Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour prompted you to pitch upon, with thoſe benefits, which you voluntarily were pleaſed to think him worthy of. My Father Sir, you did ill, and (were you not my King, I would tell you) baſely beneath your ſelfe, to mention, your ſelf occaſioning his ruine, firſt by Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſo fearefull were you of his grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſſe) and next by a State pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, procuring a forfeiture of his goods; then indeed, having made him a Beggar, you made it your charitie to afford him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66275:30"/> honourable reliefe, while the vertuous <hi>Euphrania,</hi> my Mother, and my faire Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> were forced to rely on an Annuall Penſion, ſtated upon them by my Unkle, then Duke of <hi>Fridland.</hi> For me, I acknowledge my ſelf obliged in all the bonds of Gratitude, to your Princely care: But give me leave to be ſenſible, that my Fathers Inheritance, (though it equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not the extent of an Imperiall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy in limits) had he enjoyed it, had been a Dowry ſufficient (in all reſpects) to have afforded me the ſame qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that you have beſtowed: And for the Spheare wherein I now move, I know I enjoy it altogether by your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, but I ſhould injure Heavens or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, if I ſhould make my ſelfe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that my actions have merited more then hath hitherto been conferred upon me.</p>
                  <p>How often (Sir) have I been your Bulwark, and Brazen wall, ſuppreſſing Inteſtine Commotions, and repelling for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Invaſions; how often have I
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66275:31"/> thruſt my perſon betwixt you and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? the very ſcars, (the memoriall of thoſe once gaping wounds) which in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry mortall Battailes I have received for your ſake, may plead my deſerts to be far above your rewards: Have I not (now lately) vanquiſhed, and vaſſalized, your ancient irreconcilable enemies, the <hi>Girpids,</hi> proffering to undertake ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate a ſervice, when all your paper <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's,</hi> and curtaine Champions, were devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing how to abſcond themſelves, like ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous hares, and not to meet their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, like undaunted Lions? Have not I— Hold (quoth the King) I perceive thou wilt ſoone ſhoot up (by the helpe of thine own fancie) from a pigmey, to a Piramid.</p>
                  <p>All thou haſt done, hath been but a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects duty, but I would have told you <hi>(Amandus)</hi> had not your paſſion been too predominant, over the reverence due to my perſon, that <hi>Sophronia,</hi> your Miſtreſs, (at this <hi>Amandus</hi> ſtarted) is [ſince your abſence] grown a foule looſe whore.</p>
                  <p>At this, <hi>Amandus</hi> ſtood like another
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66275:31"/> 
                     <hi>Phineas,</hi> having viewd the head of ſome <hi>Gorgon,</hi> which the King perceiving, (quoth he)</p>
                  <p>I ſay <hi>(Amandus)</hi> that your Miſtreſſe, <hi>Sophronia,</hi> is a traytreſſe to your love, and her own honour.</p>
                  <p>You would have thought <hi>Amandus</hi> had been tranſ-elemented (had you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him at that inſtant) but at length, recollecting himſelf a little, he anſwered in a diſtracted tone.</p>
                  <p>But dares <hi>Clodomer</hi> report this, and not feare a Thunder-bolt (with ſawcy <hi>Salmoneus)</hi> ſhould pound him (as <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charſis</hi> once in a morter) to peices? You are my King (Sir) I know you beare Divinitie about you, which is your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, elſe by the wronged innocence of that abuſed Lady, were you ingirt with circular flames, and managed oakes, with as much facility as children wield bulruſhes, the hilts of this ſword ſhould kiſs your heart. <hi>Sophronia</hi> falſ, I wil ſooner beleeve a Panther may be made to fetch and carry like a Spanniel; the Moone drawn down by the beating on a kettle;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66275:32"/> or conceit with a Perſpective Glaſſe to peep into Heaven, as once harbour a thought, that <hi>Sophronia</hi> can be perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                  <p>The King ſeeing him in ſuch a rage, began to doubt, that his Perſon might be endangered, and therefore thought it beſt to expoſtulate in a calme Dialect: (quoth he)</p>
                  <p>I now ſee the old Proverb verified; <hi>facile credimus, quod volumus,</hi> but let not <hi>Amandus</hi> foole himſelfe, into a faith of that which is not, if I bring thee not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent proofe, ſuch ſtrong evidence, that thy ſelfe (unleſſe madneſſe make thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous) ſhalt acknowledge, thou haſt to long been an Heritick.</p>
                  <p>Proofe (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> for Heavens ſake (Sir) delight not to torture him, that honours you; why the Angels retaine not more immaculate purity, than that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady layes claim to.</p>
                  <p>I ſee (quoth the King) it will be hard to diſ-inchaunt thee, if thou dar'ſt not give credit to my Allegation, my Son <hi>Rhoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> and honeſt <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> ſhall give thee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66275:32"/> more ample Teſtimonie.</p>
                  <p>He had no ſooner utter'd this, but <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> and <hi>Cheribrert</hi> came into the Garden, the King beckning to them to approach, which they did; <hi>Amandus</hi> not having patience, to wait the leiſure of time, went to meet them, with ſo irefull a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, that they might eaſily gueſſe the horror he had within, meeting them halfe way (quoth he) to <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sir,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I expect to find mercy at your hands, as you are noble, and have ever entertained a pleaſing thought of <hi>Amandus,</hi> tell me plainly, and poſſitively, is it in your knowledge, that my <hi>Sophronia</hi> is loſt to that goodneſſe, which once diefide her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid ſubſtance.</p>
                  <p>Yes (quoth <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> theſe eyes have ſeen that libidinous Strumpet, folded in the Armes of <hi>Cheribrerts</hi> Groom.</p>
                  <p>Too true my Lord (quoth <hi>Cheribrert)</hi> I muſt needs acknowledge, her Letcher was my Servant, a tall ſteele chind fellow (the reaſon perhaps, why ſhe affected him) but ſuch was the devotion I bare to your
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66275:33"/> name and honour (whoſe love I knew to be grounded on the firme foundation of reall worth) that I ſlew the Caitiffe with my own hands.</p>
                  <p>Peace Screitchowle (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> I know thee to be <hi>Serquilinium mendacio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> what woman may be truſted, if <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia</hi> be falſe?</p>
                  <p>Come (quoth <hi>Clodomer)</hi> let us depart to the Pallace, and there diſcourſe further of this buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>No (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> the conſtitution of my Soul agrees not with that Climate, the Pallace is ſcituate in a very noyſome peſtilentiall Aire, the Lake <hi>Avernus</hi> is Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice to it.</p>
                  <p>And ſo (with a diſtracted look, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking leave of any) he fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g away from them, departing to his Chamber, (where he found his friend <hi>Pallante;)</hi> the King, <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> and <hi>Cheribrert</hi> (not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to conſter his words at parting) departed to the Pallace, concluding (all the way they went) that <hi>Amandus</hi> muſt be ſent to his grave, or themſelves expect to lie in the Duſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:66275:33"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Sophronias <hi>complaint in priſon; her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Ghoſt appearing, forewarnes her, of future events.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Feare I have too long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to mention the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Sophronia,</hi> and therefore (if the Reader pleaſe to viſit a Priſon with me) we will walke to Caſtle <hi>Angellina,</hi> and make enquiry, how that excellent La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy brooks her reſtriction.</p>
                  <p>Who having been under the power of <hi>Janitorius</hi> (for ſo was her Keeper called) his Keys, almoſt the ſpace of twenty dayes, began (like ſome caged <hi>Philomel)</hi> to be in love with Sollitude.</p>
                  <p>Sorrow ſat in ſo lovely a ſhape upon her brow, that he that had ſeen her ſit in that ſollemn poſture, would have been enamoured on Adverſity, and (contrary to the practiſe of all mankind hitherto)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66275:34"/> have courted affliction with more affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate deſire, then young Virgins haſte to meet their beloved Paramours; ſhe bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched not forth execrations againſt <hi>Rhoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> or <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> nor taxed the Celeſtiall Powers of Tyranny, and Partiallity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking <hi>Demogorgon,</hi> or <hi>Proſerpina,</hi> but bore her Injuries like ſome captive Saint, with ſo reſolv'd and mild a Sufferance, that the moſt Inoxerable <hi>Phalaris,</hi> or <hi>Eſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lino</hi> himſelfe, would have been moved with compaſſion to have ſeen her.</p>
                  <p>One day, weary with walking to and fro in her Chamber, ſhe layd her ſelfe down on her Bed, which ſhe abundantly watered with her teares, numerouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling from the Lymbecks of her bright and heavenly eyes.</p>
                  <p>Which as they fell, <hi>Juno</hi> gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to <hi>Cupid</hi> (by the power of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head) to thread on a part of that ſtring, which loving <hi>Ariadne</hi> gave to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Theſeus</hi> (which conducted him out of the <hi>Cretan</hi> Laberinth) which ſhe wound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her Arme, tucking up her ſleeves, to ſhew her gawdy Wriſts.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:66275:34"/>
                  <p> I ſay, caſting her delicate Body on her homely Bed, ſhe began thus to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ah my deare</hi> Amandus, <hi>little doſt thou know, to what miſery thy faithfull</hi> Sophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia <hi>(for thy ſake) is expoſed; O let the whiſpering Winds convey the ſtory of my woe into thy eares, or ſome heavenly Cherub inſtruct thy intellect (for certainly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a miracle thou canſt not have notice) of my abode, in this dreadfull ominous Den; ah</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>canſt thou imagine the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpick Dieties, will ever remaine deaffe to my complaints, and not (at length in vindication of my innocency) raine</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms <hi>deſtruction, on thine, and that Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> Cheribrerts <hi>head; for if ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe ſcape unpuniſhed, then let no man tremble (for the future) to provoke the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of Heaven, by all manner of vile, and impious Acts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus ſaid, ſhe forſook the bed, and departed to that window, opening towards the Sea; ſhe had not been there long, beholding the billowes dance quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling lavaltoes, but up comes (the Kepers
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66275:35"/> wife) the old Crone that attended her, (named <hi>Morpa)</hi> with a noſegay in her hand, a bottle of wine, and a diſh of fruit, (for <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> had commanded ſhe ſhould have all civill reſpect) and ſetting them downe, making a curtſie, departed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia</hi> looking behind her, and viewing the bunch of flowers, (after ſhe had ſmelt to them) took pen, inke, and paper, and wrote this</p>
                  <lg>
                     <head>ODE</head>
                     <l>For to perfume our burying,</l>
                     <l>All the flowers of the Spring</l>
                     <l>Doe meet; man flouriſhes a time,</l>
                     <l>And theſe have but their growing prime.</l>
                     <l>Wee'r ſet, we grow, we turn to earth,</l>
                     <l>Such is our progreſſe from our birth.</l>
                     <l>Adiew all ſenſuall appetites,</l>
                     <l>Adiew ye Courts, and all delights;</l>
                     <l>The ſweeteſt breath, and cleareſt eye,</l>
                     <l>Have no perpetuitie.</l>
                     <l>As ſhadowes wait upon the Sun,</l>
                     <l>This is conſequently done.</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:66275:35"/>
                     <l> Who'd ſeek by Trophis, and dead things,</l>
                     <l>(Like ſome vaine, ambitious Kings)</l>
                     <l>To leave a living name behind?</l>
                     <l>Hoping in bags to catch the wind.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Having finiſhed theſe verſes, ſhe threw away the paper, and in a very penſive manner ſate her downe in a chaire, lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Alablaſter Face on her Ivory Hand, on one ſide of the Table, finding her ſelf much diſpoſed to ſleep.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Morpheus</hi> had ſcarce ſeized on his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Mace, with an intent to make prize of her ſenſes, when ſhe heard the noiſe of many inſtruments, conſpiring in one concord, to make a Coeleſtiall harmony, to her great admiration, which cauſed her to liſten very attentively, when on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the perfect ſhape and ſimilitude of her deceaſed mother, the (ſometime) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Euphrania,</hi> appeared to her view, apparralled all in white, her countenance the ſame when living, but more bright and poliſhed, who ſpake to her after this manner.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66275:36"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>From high</hi> Olimpus <hi>I am come,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ever bleſt</hi> Elizium,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For to forewarne thee what ſhall be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy Fate, for the futuritie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Amandus <hi>(thy eſpouſed Lord)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hath quel'd the</hi> Girpids <hi>by his ſword;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now's in</hi> Verona, <hi>feeles much ſmart,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And woe, not knowing where thou art.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Rhoxenor <hi>triumphs in his ill;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cheribrert <hi>laughs, to have his will:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But all the heavenly powers agree</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Puniſhment for their treacherie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lucinda <hi>ſhall, forfeit her breath,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>While ſhe bewailes</hi> Rhoxenors <hi>death:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And then, if thou applaud the thing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt be partner with a King.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When many ſorrowes thou haſt paſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Expect triumphant joy at laſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Having ſaid this, <hi>Euphrania's Genius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from her (ſo ſhadowes glide, and clouds vaniſh) leaving her in a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Rapture; where alſo I am compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to let her remaine a while without no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, for <hi>Amandus</hi> deeds call upon me for divulgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:66275:36"/>
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amandus (beleeving</hi> Sophronia <hi>to be falſe) is very invective againſt women.</hi> Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante <hi>defends them.</hi> Flavia <hi>(poiſoned by</hi> Cheribrert) <hi>ere ſhe dies, diſcovers the villanie of</hi> Rhoxenor <hi>and</hi> Cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brert, <hi>to</hi> Amandus. <hi>His Reſolution thereupon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU heard before, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> had left the King, the Prince, and <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> in the Privy Garden, and was returned to his chamber in great perplexity.</p>
                  <p>Where being arrived, he found his friend <hi>Pallante</hi> buſie in making verſes, (for he was an indifferent good Poet, affecting the Muſes more then (perhaps) they affected him) who, ſeeing him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in ſo diſtracted a manner, looking as he had been affrighted with ſome hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Feinds, he began to enter into dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66275:37"/> with him, imploring him to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, what uncouth accident had ſo amazed his Senſes, but not one word did <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> retribute, but throwing himſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bed, he tore his haire, and ſmote his breſt, in ſo ruthfull a manner, that <hi>Pallante</hi> could not forbeare to ſhed ſtore of teares, to behold his friend in ſuch anguiſh.</p>
                  <p>After he had a long time wrought his owne diſtemperature, he burſt forth into theſe expreſſions.</p>
                  <p>Oh wretched <hi>Sophronia,</hi> thy faithleſſe heart hath wrought my temporall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ruine; I might have been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned, by the Example of King <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Olympia; Paris</hi> and <hi>Helena; Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> and <hi>Roſana; Hercules</hi> and <hi>Dejani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra; Hannibal</hi> and <hi>Tamyra; Anthony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra; Nero</hi> and <hi>Agrippina;</hi> how I repoſed confidence in ſo weake a piece, as <hi>Sophronia:</hi> who would give credit to the proteſtations of ſo fraile, and foule a thing, as woman?</p>
                  <p>Whoſe lives are filthy; whoſe perſons without ſhame: falſe in their words;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66275:37"/> doubtfull in their acts; in whom, wiſe men ever found peril, and fooles ſuffer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie.</p>
                  <p>I now am content to credit that fond legend of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> amongſt whom it is a received opinion; <hi>That the River</hi> Nilus <hi>breaking forth, over-run the Earth, and that certaine pieces thereof, cleaving together, the Sun-beames fervently refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thereon, produced many wild beaſts, and amongſt them, was found the firſt woman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fie for ſhame (ſaid <hi>Pallante)</hi> are you not aſham'd to vent forth ſuch execrable blaſphemy, againſt that Divine, and more then Angelicall Sex.</p>
                  <p>Oh (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> could'ſt thou be capable (friend) of the miſery that I ſuffer, (exeeding that of <hi>Ixion,</hi> or <hi>Titius)</hi> thou wouldſt ſay I had cauſe to be Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall. Could hell contrive a more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative miſchief, then that ſhe, whom I affected dearer then my own life, a Lady of ſuch high Birth, and (ere this) of ſuch ſuperiour Eminency, that Princes have conteſted for her favour, glad to purchaſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66275:38"/> her ſmiles with the forfeiture of their Crownes, ſhould proſtitute her ſilken limbs to the ſordid uſe of a dirty droyle, whoſe living ſprung out of the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dung? Horror, horror.</p>
                  <p>Having thus ſaid, he began anew to practiſe violence upon his owne perſon, raving, and foaming ſo, that <hi>Pallante</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fear the loſſe of his ſenſes; and therefore ſitting down by his beds ſide, he began thus to ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>My Lord (quoth he) I beſeech you, be not ſo much the Author of your own dolour; how know you, but your <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia</hi> is guiltleſly calumniated, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed?</p>
                  <p>(Quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> Hell, and Furies, the Prince <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> and Lord <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> ſurpriſed her in the very act of ſhame.</p>
                  <p>My Lord (quoth <hi>Pallante)</hi> becauſe they ſay it, therefore will you credit it? Obſerve the circumſtances, and you will find you have great cauſe, maturely to deliberate, and ſtrictly to ſcrutinize, ere you give your cenſure. I cannot, nor dare not ſuſpect the Prince, as conſcious
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66275:38"/> of any ignoble Act: But for <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> I dare call him villaine to his face; (you know that he hath ever hated you) and who knowes whether that malicious <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca-daemon</hi> hath not contrived this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot? I am ſure you have not yet ſeen <hi>Sophronia,</hi> ſince your returne to <hi>Verona;</hi> what injuſtice then is it, for you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce your doom, ere you have heard the party accuſed ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſpeak'ſt very well, and notably to the purpoſe, my excellent Friend, (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> I confeſſe I was too raſh, although (I fear) not too confident. Having ſaid this, he deſerted the bed, calling for wine, and drinking freely with his friend, both ſitting downe by a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where <hi>Amandus</hi> found <hi>Pallante's</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Verſes, in which (himſelfe now being in Love) he had made <hi>Aericina's</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Sonne, to give this Invitation, to all Lovers, within a flight ſhot of him.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:66275:39"/>
                     <head>CUPIDS <hi>Invitation to his BOWER.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <head type="sub">ODE.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LOve expels all cares and feares,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With muſick that out-vies the Spheres;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And with Soule-melting Lullabies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Doth calme all paſsions that ariſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which give a motion to the Stones,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With their ſweet alluring Tones.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hands, and lips, and eyes invite,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>See the ſnowy Virgins white.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here's many</hi> Alexanders <hi>brave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As many</hi> Hellens <hi>faire I have,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Only for to wait on me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They attired richly be.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You ſhall have her in plenty, laviſh</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whatſoe're the Senſe can raviſh.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Driades <hi>have ſtolen by theft</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To me, and their green Groves have left;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And in this my Bower green,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sol, Neptune, Thetis, <hi>have been ſeen.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I can give you</hi> Tagus <hi>Sand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Never ſaile out of the Land.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:66275:39"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>I have golden Fleeces ſtore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Never goe to</hi> Cholchos <hi>ſhoare.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Elizian <hi>Fields are in my plaine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore the ſhades you haunt in vaine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Jove <hi>to me his Court doth bring,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With his</hi> Ganimeds <hi>to ſing.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Careleſſe of</hi> Argus <hi>hundred eyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or of jealous</hi> Juno's <hi>Spies.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For nothing elſe the Gods made night,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But for to ſcreene Eovers delight.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus</hi> having read theſe Verſes, (quoth he) I find (friend <hi>Pallante)</hi> that you are very amorouſly inclin'd, and write with a Quill, pluck'd even from <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pids</hi> wing. My <hi>Genius</hi> ever led me to (that with which my preſent condition beſt ſuites) Solid and Grave Subjects, dreſſed in Proſe: But that you may ſee I have ſipt off <hi>Hellicon,</hi> and ſlept ſome minutes on <hi>Parnaſſus;</hi> I will endeavour, (by the help of the nine) to write ſome few numbers. I have now to doe with Tombs, and Death-beds; Funerals, and Teares; ſo fetching a Deaths head, which he alwayes gave a reſidence (nocturnally)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:66275:40"/> by him, he ſet it down before him on the Table, and wrote theſe Verſes;</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though here on earth men differ, in the grave</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There's no diſtinction; all alike they have.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then muſt the Conqueror, with the captive ſpred,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>On one bare earth, as in the common bed</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The all commanding Generall hath no ſpan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of ground allowd, more then a common man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Folly with Wiſedome hath an equall ſhare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The foul, and faire, to like duſt changed are.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This is, of all mortality, the end:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Therſites <hi>now with</hi> Nereus <hi>dares contend;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And with</hi> Achilles <hi>he hath equall place,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That living, durſt not look him in the face.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ſervant with his Maſter, and the maid,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Stretch'd by her Miſtreſs; both their heads are laid</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Upon an equal pillow; ſubjects keep</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Courts, with Kings equal, &amp; as ſoft they ſleep,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lodging their heads upon a turfe of graſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As they on Marble, or on figur'd braſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>He had ſcarce finiſhed theſe Verſes, when <hi>Flavia, (Sophronia's</hi> quondam wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing woman) came in, in great haſt, and falling downe at his feet, beſought
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66275:40"/> him to hear her a few words, and to give credit to her laſt breath, for (quoth ſhe) I feele the poiſon powerfully to oppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. Speak (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> ere thou catch an everlaſting cold, and ſhalt be heard no more, what important matter doth thy tongue labour with.</p>
                  <p>(Quoth ſhe) it is not unknowne to you, that I once ſerved your vertuous <hi>Sophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> (I muſt be briefe in my diſcovery) as became her, in whom ſhe repoſed ſo great confidence, and had ſtill continued her loyall Servitrex, had not the black Soul'd <hi>Cheribrert</hi> deluded me, to my deſtruction and her ruine; who knowing himſelfe not able to win me to ſatiate his luſt (and knowing I would not deny him lawfull love) perſwaded me he meant to make me his Wife, enjoyning me (as the firſt tryall of my love) to aid him in the proſecution of a buſineſſe; for the fulfilling whereof, he had ſtrongly engaged himſelfe, which was, (O Sir, pardon my trercherous Levity) to admit Prince <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> [who, he ſaid, was greatly enamoured on <hi>Sophronia]</hi> to her Bed; this I was wonne to, but the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66275:41"/> devilliſh <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> did but feign this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to me; for he ſo ordered it, that his Groom (whom he afterwards ſlew with his own hands, for fear his villany might be detected) entred the Chamber, and the Innocent <hi>Sophronia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She would have proceeded, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous potion had by this time ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled her facculties, that ſhe fell down all along, and (with a feeble tone, uſing theſe words; <hi>My Lord, be aſſured, that</hi> Sophronia <hi>is the moſt vertuous Lady in the world. I would diſcover more, but the Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath diſperſed it ſelfe all over my heart; I am the occaſion of all this ill, and goe, I know not whether)</hi> with a greivous groan dyed.</p>
                  <p>What pen can expreſſe, or what heart thinke, the extream aſtoniſhment that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to <hi>Amandus,</hi> to heare theſe dying words of <hi>Flavia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh yee Immortall Powers (quoth he) what fatall end have yee reſerved me for, have I eſcaped the <hi>Girpids</hi> fury, and ſwam a Sea of blood (like another <hi>Coeſar,</hi> with one hand cutting my paſſage through the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66275:41"/> Waves, and holding in the other, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of Peace and Tranquility) to my native Country, to be put upon the defiance of my Soveraignes Sonne, whom to challenge I dare not [the Law making ſuch a propoſall, the higheſt Treaſon] was this <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> revenge for <hi>Sophroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> deniall, to proſtitute her immaculate Chaſtity, to his rapide Luxury, conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with that Hell hound <hi>Cheribrert,</hi> to ruine her life and fame, and in her, my name and honour.</p>
                  <p>This I Prognoſticated (quoth <hi>Pallante)</hi> and durſt have divulged it, though I could not deſert the ſeverall circumſtances, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you have heard them narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <p>Oh (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> can <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> be ſo treacherous, he that was once ſo excellently good, now ſo diabollically vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; Heaven knows where they have diſpoſed my ſouls life, and the glory of her Sex, the vertuous <hi>Sophronia;</hi> but I procraſtinate the time too long, dares <hi>Pallante</hi> ſwear to joyn with his friend, in a noble and juſt revenge.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:66275:42"/>
                  <p> Dares (quoth <hi>Pallante)</hi> you wrong your own judgement and my fidellity; if you are maſter of one anxious thought, were I to follow thee (like another <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus</hi> with his <hi>Hercules)</hi> to the black and diſmall ſhades of <hi>Dis;</hi> or (with <hi>Oreſtes</hi> and his other ſelfe) to give and receive Death, we falling by mutuall wounds, to put a period to our terreſtiall terrors, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> ſhould finde me every way pliable to his own wiſh.</p>
                  <p>Spoke like a true friend (quoth <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus)</hi> and then kneeling down <hi>(Pallante</hi> accompanying him) he drew forth his Sword, and laying their hands upon the Weapon [like another <hi>Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine]</hi> they joyntly Swore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Never to permit the cloſure of their eyes, till they had wiped away</hi> Sophronias <hi>ſtaine, with Spunges, made of the hearts of</hi> Rhox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enor <hi>and</hi> Cheribrert.</p>
                  <p>So kiſſing the Hilts, they aroſe, of whom read more in the following Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:66275:42"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Amandus <hi>kils</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>the manner thereof; he and</hi> Pallante <hi>eſcape.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was ſomewhat late in the evening, when <hi>Flavia</hi> made her eſcape to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus,</hi> and therefore it was unknown, whither ſhe had conveyed her ſelf, though <hi>Cheribrert</hi> had ſent Inquiſitors all about the City; and being conſcious of his own guilt, and timerous, that <hi>Flavia</hi> had diſcovered all ſhe knew, he reſolved to ſteale forth the City that night, only himſelf and one Servant, on horſeback, taking with him, ſtore of Gold and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (the occaſion of his after ruine,) where I leave him to the horror of his own thoughts, and return to <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who imagining (as indeed it was) that (perhaps) <hi>Flavia</hi> was not noted (becauſe of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:66275:43"/> the darkneſſe of the night) to take her journey to them, they reſolved to bury her privately (which they did, throwing her into a deep Well, near adjacent to the houſe) and to take no notice (for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) of her diſcovery, till they ſhould finde opportune admittance to <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>That night they paſſed away, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on various Subjects, ſometimes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> pravation, another time plottiug, how they might infranchiſe <hi>Sopbronia;</hi> but <hi>Aurora</hi> appearing [in the Horizon, with her purple hair hanging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her eares, which ſhe was ſoon forced to ſeclude, under an azure cawle, for fear <hi>Sol</hi> ſhould findge them with his beams] they both armed themſelves; <hi>Amandus</hi> commanding his Caroach to be fitted (with his friend) entred therein, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Chariot driver, to direct his way towards the Pallace.</p>
                  <p>There arived, they disburthened the Caroach of their perſons, and walking on foot to the Pallace Gate, the Guard (knowing them to be Perſonages emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66275:43"/> gracious in the Kings eye) gave them free admittance.</p>
                  <p>So they paſſed forwards, towards <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> lodgings with like facillity, all offering them conduct, till they came even to <hi>Rhoxenors</hi> Chamber, who the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O the fatallity, that governes ſome mens actions) had been guilty of that, which he never before was noted for, <hi>viz.</hi> exceſſive tipling, which he had ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly plyed, that he was conveyed to his Pallace (the night before) in a drunken dreame, to which ſtupidity, he was yet vaſſalized; <hi>Amandus</hi> (preſuming on his owne eminent familiarity with the Prince) comes to the Chamber doore, demanding entrance, the Chamberlain wondered at ſuch an unwonted demand (more Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies uſually obſerved, ere the Prince was to be ſpoke withall) demanded who was there.</p>
                  <p>'Tis I (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> and my friend <hi>Pallante,</hi> who deſire permiſſion to ſpeak with the Prince, about important buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>The Chamberlain (knowing <hi>Amandus</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:66275:44"/> voyce) opened the door, and <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante</hi> entring in, the Chamberlain (to ſhew himſelfe too obſequiouſly officious, as not daring to prie into their privicies) left the room, and ſo (as it happened) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed his life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus</hi> (perceiving <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> aſleep) at his entrance uſed theſe words to <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>See (quoth he) how ſupinely this perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Prince ſleeps, who could immagine this beautifull Image, included ſuch an ugly Feind within it? I will kill him thus ſleeping, and ſend his leprous ſoul to Hell, ere <hi>Pluto</hi> expect it.</p>
                  <p>By no meanes (quoth <hi>Pallante)</hi> let his own tongue firſt doom him, ere you give him his paſſe for the other world.</p>
                  <p>With that <hi>Amandus</hi> indeavoured to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake him, crying, my Lord, my Lord, the Prince.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> opening his eyes, and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> by his Beds ſide, a ſtrange &amp; unwonted feare ſeized on him (as if by inſtinct he had known their intents) but he would not ſeem to be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:66275:44"/> and therefore replyed.</p>
                  <p>Noble <hi>Amandus,</hi> worthy <hi>Pallante,</hi> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, what buſineſſe more then ordinary, hath brought you hither, ſo early in the morning?</p>
                  <p>Your highneſſe (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> errs in the computation of time, for the Sunne hath already meaſured almoſt a thouſand leagues; the reaſon of my abrupt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, is occaſioned by a Dream I had this night, concerning <hi>Sophronia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia</hi> (quoth <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> let the name of that Purple Strumpet be loſt to your memory; I wonder you are ſo ſlow to bring her to condigne puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Oh the Devil (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> doſt thou hear this <hi>Pallante,</hi> and with that word pulling a Dagger out of his pocket, thou ſtaine to the Stock of Kings (quoth he) the hand of Truth hath puld of thy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, I am acquainted with thy clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine projections, with that villain <hi>Cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brert,</hi> I know thy attempting <hi>Sophronias</hi> Chaſtity, her deniall, and thy ignoble revenge.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:66275:45"/>
                  <p> And with that word he ſtabd the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard up the hilts in his ſhort ribs, which wounded him greiviouſly but not deadly.</p>
                  <p>Oh hold thy hand (quoth <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> I confeſſe I have been (as thou thy ſelf art at preſent) to much a ſlave to my paſſions, and have indeavoured the ruine of the moſt noble Lady in the world.</p>
                  <p>For which (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> I thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice thee on the Altar of revenge (no other way viſſible ſuiting with my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents) and therewith again ſtabbed him with his Ponniard, through the throat, which occaſioned an egreſſion of all the breath in his body, ſo that after a little ſtrugling, he became ſoulleſſe.</p>
                  <p>By this time the Chamberlain was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to know the Princes pleaſure, in order to his Apparell for that day, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the door, &amp; perceiving <hi>Amundus,</hi> his face beſprinkled, and his hands bedew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with blood, he took a large leap back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, more then twenty paces, crying, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon, Treaſon, the Prince is murtherd, the Prince is murtherd:</hi> whereat the Kings Guard, in great aſtoniſhment,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:66275:45"/> drawing their ſwords, came towards <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xenors</hi> lodgings, and were encountred halfe way by <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> with their weapons drawne, the Guard not doubting to make prize of their perſons, cryed out to them to yeild themſelves, but were ſoone taught to know, that <hi>Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men, goe doubly Arm'd:</hi> Some had their hands, others their legs, and ſome their noſes pared away; others lay vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out their heart blouds; none, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſabled by wounds, or by death.</p>
                  <p>So that <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> had time to make their eſcape into the City, where arrived, <hi>Amandus</hi> cryed all the way, <hi>Thoſe that love me, follow me.</hi> The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (who entirely affected him) arming themſelves, followed him in heaps. <hi>Venantius,</hi> and <hi>Palladius,</hi> (as luck was, not having yet made riddance of their lately received Arrears) were tipling in a Taverne, and hearing the noiſe of the people, and eſpying <hi>Amandus</hi> (all bloudy) with his ſword drawne, waited on by an armed multitude, they began to ſing pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to the blind Goddeſſe, <hi>Fortune,</hi> and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:66275:46"/> the great Sword-man, <hi>Mars,</hi> that once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain they were like to have employment in the heart of their native Countrey; and thruſting themſelves into the midſt of the preaſe, they proffered their ſervice to <hi>Amandus,</hi> who kindly accepted them; with whom I leave them, and returne to the body of dead <hi>Rhoxenor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Confuſion of the Court and City, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rumour of</hi> Rhoxenors <hi>Death.</hi> Lucinda <hi>dies (with griefe) over her dead Sonne. The City being divided, the one part for</hi> Amandus; <hi>the other for</hi> Clodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; <hi>there happeneth a ſoure Skirmiſh.</hi> Amandus, <hi>and</hi> Pallante, <hi>taking an Arme of the Sea, recover the Kingdome of</hi> Polonia.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch a confuſed clamour as men make when eager fire hath fallen upon many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks at once, in ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous City, <hi>Mulciber</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:66275:46"/> the Heavens; or ſuch a Tragick tone, as the Inhabitants of ſome beſieged Town accord in, when their Furious E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are already entred their Chiefe Fort; Slaughter, and Rapine, Revelling in each corner: Such, and no other, was the wild Alarme given throughout the Court, and City, men mingled together in multitudes, but the more part knew not wherefore they were met together, the Courtiers being afraid every man of his fellow, and the Citizens expecting every minute to be buried in their own ruines.</p>
                  <p>Newes being brought to <hi>Clodomer</hi> and <hi>Lucinda,</hi> of the murther of their Sonne, (by their Generall <hi>Amandus</hi> hand) Grief, and Wonder (like two contrary winds ſtriving for Soveraignty) a long time maintained a Civil War within them; but at length, Griefe got the upper hand, and ſo prevailed over their Senſes, that for ſome minutes, their tongues wanted the uſe of their Creation; but at length, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering themſelves, (like another di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed <hi>Priam,</hi> with his forlorne <hi>Hecuba)</hi> they ſet forward, to viſit their dead Son,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:66275:47"/> whom when they beheld, what griping pangs their hearts endured, only thoſe can imagine, whom Fate hath expoſed to the like affliction. <hi>Clodomer</hi> could not ſpeak for weeping; but <hi>Lucinda,</hi> falling upon her dead Sonne, tore her haire, bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his bloudy wounds, with briny drops, making this pitifull complaint over him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ah my deare Sonne (ſaid ſhe) is this the fulfilling of that expectation, my Selfe, thy Father, and all</hi> Lombardy <hi>had cauſe to have of thee? Could the cruell Deſtinies finde no other ſubject whereon to practice their Tyranny, ſave thee? Poore</hi> Lucinda! <hi>why did</hi> Lucina <hi>(pitying thy pangs) propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly ayd thee, for the production of a Son, predeſtinated to ſo direfull an</hi> exit?</p>
                  <p>She would have ſaid more, but the greatneſſe of her grief, at once bereft her, both of ſpeech, and life, ſo that ſhe fell down dead by her murthered Son.</p>
                  <p>This to behold, ſo exaſperated the King <hi>Clodomer,</hi> that like one bereft of his wits, he ran raving up and down the City, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching his ſubjects to take pity on their diſteſſed Soveraigne, and unanimouſly to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:66275:47"/> ayd him, in the diſcovery of <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> who had at once bereft them of a moſt hopefull Prince, and a gracious Queen.</p>
                  <p>It was not long ere he had levied a Power, which he put under the command of <hi>Lucius,</hi> and <hi>Pamelius,</hi> (ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Captaines, though now by reaſon of their Age, they affected privacie) who marſhalling his Forces, marched towards <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante;</hi> who, with their handfull of men, had intrenched them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on a plaine, three Leagues diſtant from the City: The King himſelfe (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to fight in perſon leading them on as their chief Guide, and Captain.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus</hi> perceiving their approach, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to give them Battell, and diſpoſed his Forces accordingly.</p>
                  <p>Both Armies being now ſo neare one another, that they might eaſily heare the diſputes paſſing on both ſides; the King chuſing a piece of ground, by nature ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated above the reſt of the continent, ſo that he might ſee (and be ſeen) of his whole Army, began to ſay as followeth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:66275:48"/> I <hi>Dare be confident, that none of my loyall Subjects here, who (according to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) are congregated with me, for the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating, and puniſhing the treacherous, bloudy-minded</hi> Amandus, <hi>and his trayterous Aſſociate,</hi> Pallante, <hi>but are able and willing to atteſt, with what Gentleneſſe, and Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall care</hi> (as becommeth the Father of his Countrey) <hi>I have hitherto governed them: As alſo, what an hopefull Prince, and what promiſing Vertues were obvious in my Son</hi> Rhoxenor; <hi>and that my Queen,</hi> Lucinda, <hi>excelled all former Queenes, for the Love, and affectionate Zeale ſhe demonſtrated to me, her King, and Husband, and to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Nation; both which, are made away by meanes of the afore-mentioned Traytors. Therefore, I ſhall not endeavour with elaborate orarory (my loyall Subjects) to kindle courage in your hearts, or to make you ſenſible, that (beſides the loſſe) great, and infinite ſhame, not to be expiated by any after performances, will brand us all with the deepeſt tincture of infamy, unleſſe we take juſt (but ſevere vengeance) on theſe ſanguine homicides. Not doubting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:66275:48"/> 
                     <hi>of your courage in ſo good a cauſe, goe on, and may Heaven crown your attempts with Victory.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>Neither was <hi>Amandus</hi> ſlack to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his men, but ſtanding in the midſt of them, made this Oration.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>My fellow Subjects,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>VVHom Love to wronged</hi> Amandus, <hi>(and in him to Juſtice, and Honour) hath invited to hazard your Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; be confident, that I deſire not War, or have requeſted your Ayd, for the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of any private grudge, or ſiniſter ends of mine owne, but meerly for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my own Perſon, and your Rights; both which (unleſſe defenſive armes prevent it) are like to be ſwallowed up, in that bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe gulfe of Kingly Prerogative, and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power. It is not unknown to you (I am ſure) with what faithfulneſs I have ever ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this faithleſſe King; how often I have brought him home conqueſt, putting the necks of his enemies under his feet: And is it my reward, to have her, whom I love dearer then my life, (whoſe Vertues are ſo</hi>
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:66275:49"/> 
                        <hi>ſplendid, that envy it ſelf cannot fully them) thrown into a naſty Gaole, and branded with the ignominious Epethites of Whoore, and Strumpet, and all, becauſe ſhe denied to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate</hi> Rhoxenors <hi>beaſtly Luſt, whom Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and not my hand, hath ſent to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World. If this be tolerated, not one of you here preſent, ſhall claime the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in her whom he affecteth. Time will not permit me to dilate my ſelf, ſuffice, you fight with me in a juſt and righteous cauſe; the truth whereof, I hope your ſwords will prove, (though your enemies treble you in number) On then couragiouſly in the name of Heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Having finiſhed this Oration, he led on his Army to joyn Battell with the Kings, dividing them (being all foot) into foure Battailes: The firſt, himſelf guided; the ſecond, <hi>Pallante</hi> took charge of; and the third, and fourth, followed <hi>Venantius,</hi> and <hi>Palladius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clodomer</hi> ordered his Army (after the old Roman manner) in the faſhion of an half-moone; the hornes whereof, were managed by <hi>Lucius,</hi> and <hi>Pamelius,</hi> and the main Body, by himſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:66275:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> Both Armies joyning, it was <hi>Amandus</hi> hap to encounter <hi>Lucius;</hi> and <hi>Pallante, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius;</hi> all (ſave the King, being on foot on both ſides, for the ſuddenneſſe of the action would not permit the mounting of men, or to obſerve the method of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Diſcipline.) <hi>Amandus</hi> had ſoon made an end of <hi>Lucius,</hi> cleaving his head, that his brains dropt out at his feet; and <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante</hi> had given <hi>Pamelius</hi> ſo deadly a blow on the face, that he cut his jawes clean in ſunder. The King <hi>Clodomer</hi> ſhewed himſelf very valiant, with his own hands having killed <hi>Venantius,</hi> and <hi>Palladius,</hi> and maſſacred above an hundred of the vulgar ſort, white <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> mowed down all before them, ſo that their hands were weary of the work of death, their weapons were drunk with bloud, and their bodies were burdened with bloud and ſweat; ſo that, notwithſtanding their forces were clean cut in peices, (being raw, unexperienced ſouldiers, meere Citizens, who till now had never been accuſtomed to the rigour of War) they had, by their ſingle valours, vanquiſhed the Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:66275:50"/> and taken himſelfe Priſoner, had not an huge multitude (from the City) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to his reliefe, armed with prongs, pitchforks, and bils, who come on ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, that it was impoſſible, (and had been madneſſe) to oppoſe them: And therefore (overpowred with numbers) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> having even then encountred <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer</hi> on foot, and forced him to forſake his horſe (who was preſently protected by thoſe about him) leapt into the Saddle, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Pallante</hi> up behind him, being forced (on a deſperate adventure) to take an Arm of the Sea, and ſwam over, to a part of that continent belonging to the King of <hi>Polonia;</hi> and <hi>Clodomer</hi> having gained this bloudy Victory, returned (with thoſe of his Army, whom the late conflict had ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the Citie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:66275:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE LOVES OF</hi> AMANDVS <hi>AND</hi> SOPHRONIA. <hi>The Third Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Rhoxenor, <hi>and</hi> Lucinda, <hi>are ſumptuouſly Interr'd.</hi> Alphonſus <hi>(King of</hi> Poland) <hi>refuſeth to deliver up the perſons of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus, <hi>and</hi> Pallante. Sophronia, <hi>brought to her Triall, is acquitted.</hi> Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer loves her.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Lodomer,</hi> having thus vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but (to his great vexation) not captivated his enemies, cladding himſelfe in purple, (as the manner of Kings is to mourne)
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:66275:51"/> and commanding his whole Court to put on Sables, cauſed his Sonne, and Queen, to be embalmed, by the Skill of his ableſt Phyſitians, who involved them in lead, the King cauſing two Stately Tombs to be erected (of the pureſt <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Stone) framed by the hands of cunning Architectors, who adorned them ſo ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly, that either of them equalled <hi>Mauſoleus</hi> his Sepulcher, (reputed one of the wonders of the World) in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church, dedicated to the memory of St. <hi>Sebaſtiona,</hi> and <hi>Albovino,</hi> (two ancient famous Kings of that Countrey) which having finiſhed, he diſpatched Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> to let him know, that he harboured his deep enemies, <hi>viz. Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> Traytors to his Crown and Dignity, whoſe perſons (as he tendred the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of the Amity betwixt the two Crowns of <hi>Lombardie,</hi> and <hi>Poland)</hi> he willed him to deliver up to condigne puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> retaining a noble tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, (knowing <hi>Amandus</hi> to be a man eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way accompliſhed) and ſenſible of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:66275:51"/> wrongs offered by <hi>Rhoxenor,</hi> (the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration whereof, had occaſioned his death, and <hi>Amandus</hi> Infortunity) permitted <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante</hi> leſt the protecting of their perſons might draw a war upon him) to depart his Kingdome without moleſtation, furniſhing them with horſes, and Arms, and all things befitting the uſe of ſuch Knights of Fame.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Clodomer,</hi> finding he could not get their perſons into his hands, reſolved (like another ſalvage <hi>Neoptolemus,</hi> who Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed an Innocent Princeſſe on his Fathers grave) to be revenged on <hi>Sophronia, (A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> Miſtreſſe, and for his ſake impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned) for his Sons death; and therefore he appointed a day, when (accompanied with all his Nobles) he would cauſe her to be brought as a Delinquent, and proceeded againſt as a Strumpet, to publick cenſure.</p>
                  <p>And therefore he cauſed many Scaffolds to be erected in the Pallace yard, with a Seat of Judicature for himſelfe, and his Peers; where comming (with thoſe whom he had nominated for her Judges) he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her to be guarded from priſon,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:66275:52"/> thither, as the place appointed for her trial.</p>
                  <p>The moſt vertuous <hi>Sophronia,</hi> having newes brought her the night before, that ſhe was to prepare her ſelf againſt the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to plead before the King, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, was not a whit daunted thereat, <hi>(ſo great courage doth Innocencie inject, and ſo ſtrongly are thoſe fortified againſt mundane calamities, whoſe ſoules aſſure them they are falſly calumniated)</hi> but attired her ſelfe all in black, with a veile of the ſame colour caſt over her head, which habit was ſo far from eclipſing, that it added to her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Splendor; as Diamonds ſet in Jet, are not a whit darkned; nor doth the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paz loſe its Luſtre, though ſet in lead.</p>
                  <p>In this manner, ſhe ſet forward with her Guard, (never was ſo ſweet a priſoner brought to the Bar, a thouſand <hi>Cupids</hi> (though unſeen) waited on her all the way; <hi>Venus</hi> her ſelf wept, and the Graces, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doled her afflictions, in ſanguine teares; the people thronging in heapes to ſee her, yet amongſt that multitude, not a dry eye: Such a ſilent mourning as the <hi>Grecians</hi> practiſed, when they beheld <hi>Agamemnons</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:66275:52"/> daughter, faire <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> in funerall attire, ſtanding at the Altar, ready to be Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to <hi>Aeolus,</hi> was heard amongſt this people; every one aſſoiling her Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and bewailing her miſery.</p>
                  <p>Comming to the place appointed, ſhe was placed at the Bar, where turning up her veile, and diſcovering her rare Beauty, which was ſo celeſtially ſplendid, that it caſt a light round about her, (all mens eies being fixed upon her, as if ſome ſhaghair'd Comet had thruſt forth his head in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere.) The King was exceedingly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed to behold her, the fire of love burnt about his heart, by degrees corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating more and more, till it became one flaming lump of fleſh; his colour went and came, a kind of trembling ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon all his body: But diſguiſing his paſſions as well as he could, he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her Charge to be read, which contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe two Heads;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That ſhe had been guilty of Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie with Lord</hi> Cheribrerts <hi>Groome, being taken in the very act of ſhame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That ſhe had plotted, and conſpired</hi>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:66275:53"/> 
                     <hi>with</hi> Amandus, <hi>and</hi> Pallante, <hi>(Capitall Traytors and guilty of the horrid murther (poſsitively) of Prince</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>(conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) of the Queen</hi> Lucinda, <hi>and (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) of Lord</hi> Cheribrert) <hi>for the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration and performance, of the aforeſaid treaſonable, devilliſh, and unparell'd crimes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this, after a little pauſe (making o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſance to the King and Counſell) ſhe anſwered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That I may not be condemned as a Mute, and becauſe the Party ſilent, is thought to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to what ever is propoſed; I wil breifly, though ſincerely, make my defence in the preſence of the high Immortall Truth, and this Aſſembly, elſe I could have been conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have ſuffered in ſilence, aſſuring my ſelfe, that before the Judge of Soules I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare immaculately Innocent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My converſation from my Infancy, till of late months (aſſure my ſelfe) is not unknown to many here; I have indeavoured alwaies, to accrew an unſpotted Fame, and (I doubt not) had retained the ſame, to this very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, had it not thus happened.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here ſhe ſurveyed the Counſell (and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:66275:53"/> being ignorant of what had lately happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) not ſeeing <hi>Rhoxenor</hi> there, demanded that he might be brought before her, face to face.</p>
                  <p>To which the King <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>though his thoughts told him ſhe was innocent) returned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That her pollicy could not wipe away her guilt, ſhe knew, that</hi> Rhoxenor <hi>(as ſhe had plotted with the curſed Traytor</hi> Amandus) <hi>was cruelly murthered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which (with a ſober ſmile) ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be it knowne unto all here, that Lord</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus, <hi>being abſent in the wars, againſt the</hi> Girpids, <hi>in the defence of his Country (unto whom I acknowledge my ſelfe affian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) the Prince</hi> Rhoxenor, <hi>finding that all his perſwaſive allurements were to weak, to remove my firme fixed conſtancy (conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with Lord</hi> Cheribrert, <hi>a man ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively wicked) by a treacherous wile [ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving corrupted the faith of my waiting-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Flavia] <hi>hath wrought the preſent ruine of my fame and honour (by</hi> Flavias <hi>aide) they one night entred my Chamber (my ſelf</hi>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:66275:54"/> 
                     <hi>faſt aſleep) bringing with them, a fellow (whom they had ſubborned for that purpoſe) who entred my Bed, which he had no ſooner done, but</hi> Rhoxenor <hi>and</hi> Cheribrert <hi>(as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had plotted) with loud cries awaked me, upbraiding me with lewdneſſe, and term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me the blot, and ſtain of all Ladies in the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And leſt the fellow (moved with remorſe or otherwiſe) ſhould reveale their curſed complot,</hi> Cheribrert <hi>with his own hands, immediately ſtab'd his hireling to the heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rhoxenor <hi>having wrought this villany, ſo wrought, that I was committed (as a vile perſon) to Caſtle</hi> Angellina, <hi>where I have ever ſince reſided.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the murther of <hi>Rhoxenor, Lucinda,</hi> and <hi>Cheribrert</hi> (if it be ſo, which Heaven forbid) the ſtraitneſſe of my reſtraint, none having been ſuffered to come near me, ſave my Keeper, ſince my reſtriction, may plead my innocency in that matter.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Sophronia</hi> uttered with a very audible voice, and having finiſhed, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gave a ſhout, crying, <hi>She is innocent, ſhe is innocent;</hi> which alſo was the ſenſe of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:66275:54"/> the whole Counſell, <hi>Clodomer</hi> himſelf (though he ſeemed otherwiſe) being glad of it, for he was extreamly in love with her.</p>
                  <p>The Court riſing, <hi>Sophronia</hi> (by the Kings command) was conducted to the Pallace, of whom more hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The dreadfull end of</hi> Cheribrert. Amandus <hi>and</hi> Pallante, <hi>leaving</hi> Poland <hi>[being bound for</hi> Venice] <hi>by an angry Storme, are forced on the coaſts of</hi> Grecia <hi>(the Ship and all elſe ſwallowed in the Waves) they ſave themſelves by ſwimming, and arive on the</hi> Flowry Iland.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow it is high time that I made mention, what became of <hi>Cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brert,</hi> after his deſerting <hi>Verona</hi> (as you have heard) by night, accompanied only with one Servant.</p>
                  <p>He had not travailed many miles, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to take his journey, to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt borders of the Kingdom of <hi>Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:66275:55"/> and ſo take ſhipping for <hi>Spaine,</hi> but a crew of Robbers, who ſubſiſted by ſpoile and rapine, ſet upon him (imagining to finde, as indeed they did, a good booty) plundering him of all his Gold and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſtripping him, and his Servitor (who making ſome reſiſtance was ſlain) to the bare Skins.</p>
                  <p>Being brought to this miſerable exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency (inflicted upon him by divine ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance) he began to think of his many damnable crimes (yet ſo, as he not repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of them) and to curſe the houre, that ever he ingaged himſelf (with <hi>Rhoxenor)</hi> to injure the vertuous <hi>Sophronia;</hi> he would have caſt his eyes up to heaven, and have implored the remiſſion of his charnell contrivances, but he diſpaired of attaining audience, at the eares of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed Diety, and therefore ſitting him down upon the earth, he began to wiſh, that a thurderbold from Heaven might paſh him in peeces, or the earth open and receive him, when he might hear an hollow murmuring voyce, ſing him this ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:66275:55"/>
                     <l> Orcus <hi>yawnes, the furies yell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deſcend accurſed Soul to Hell;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Earth hates, thy loathed Trunk to have,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Wombs of Wolves ſhall be thy Grave.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let all take warning, by thy Fate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How they thy crimes, doe perpetrate.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>This infernall Invitation, ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed him, that he would fain have ſlain himſelf, but wanted fit meanes to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh it, and therefore the reprobate wretch, with his own nails, began to tear, and rend the ground, intending to dig his own grave; when (as if ſent by ſome avenging Diety) a crew of ravenous Wolves came running upon him, and tearing him all in peices, buried his loathed body in their hungry mawes: <hi>a dreadfull end, worthy ſo devilliſh a wretch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now ſince we have rambled ſo farre from <hi>Verona,</hi> let us ſpeak a little of the noble Knights, <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> who having left the Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> imbarqued themſelves in a Ship bound for <hi>Venice</hi> (where <hi>Pallante</hi> had an Uncle,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:66275:56"/> named <hi>D' Franciſco Mendoza,</hi> a famous Sennatour of that renowned City) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to reſide there for a time in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate (though they would not have found it eaſie, ſo to have done, <hi>Amandus</hi> acts having made him ſo renownedly famous, throughout <hi>Europe)</hi> and to wait with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience a while, to ſee what end, Fortune would put to her own prankes.</p>
                  <p>They had not ſailed farre from the Port, but the Winds began to blow very eagerly, the Marriners hoyſed all their Sailes a trip, imagining to have found cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, amidſt the uncertain Waves, when the Skies on a ſudden, were obſcured, with black and pitchie Clouds; <hi>Eurus</hi> whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering ſad tales in the Sea-mens eares; from the <hi>Altantick</hi> Ocean came <hi>Notus,</hi> bringing with him Thunder and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when to encounter him, out flies <hi>Boreas,</hi> bearing Stormes, and Tempeſts on his wings, the high wrought Seas, fronted the Skies, wrapping their liequid curles in the clouds, no Sunne, nor Moon, or Starres appearing, ſo that had <hi>Palinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> ſelf been Pilot, he could not have
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:66275:56"/> ſteer'd aright; the furious waves, ruſhing together with imbatled power, plow large furrowes in the ſides of the Ship; the boyſtrous billowes, invade, and paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her hatches, daſhing her againſt the Rocks; nor could all their pumping pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, but that each man ſtood up to the knees in water, the paſſengers all crying to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for help, in ſuch dolefull manner, that it would have compelled an heart of flint to compaſſionate them, while the Ship (droven by furious winds many thouſand leagues) was forced on the Coaſt of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Amandus</hi> found not ſo great toile without, as he found terrour within; his heart beat louder Alarms then the angry Seas, when he thought upon his dear <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia,</hi> imagining this puniſhment was ſent from Heaven for his ſake, for that he forſook <hi>Verona,</hi> ere he attempted to infranchiſe the perſon of his dearly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Lady.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Oh</hi> Sophronia (ſaid he) <hi>who knows what miſerie thou endureſt for my ſake!</hi> Clodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>will not faile to ſhed thy innocent bloud,</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:66275:57"/> 
                     <hi>in revenge of his wicked Sonne, whom I juſtly ſlew. Ah, unfortunate Lovers! thou (I feare) art ſnatch'd away already, by the hand of violence, upon the Land; and I (by deſtiny droven) muſt, ere long, periſh in this barbarous element.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pallante</hi> endeavoured all he could to comfort him. <hi>But (quoth he) it is no time now, to practice a lovers paſsion, when we expect every minute to become a prey to the devouring waves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this time the waves came in ſo faſt, hat the Ship began to ſink; and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and Pilot, ſeeing there was no hope, let downe the cock-boat into the Seas, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending (with <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to truſt to the mercy of the watry ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that dimunitive veſſell: But ſo numerous and eagre, were thoſe periſhing paſſengers in the finking Ship, (every one deſirous to preſerve his life) that though they endeavoured to hinder their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with their ſwords drawn, they could not, but that the little Skiffe, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with numbers, choſe rather to be choaked with the ſalt Seas, then harbour ſuch mercileſſe oppreſſors.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:66275:57"/>
                  <p> But <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> (being well skilled in ſwimming) periſhed not amongſt the reſt, but bore up above water, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king way with their hands and feet, (while <hi>Neptune</hi> with all his <hi>Tritons</hi> gazed upon them, imagining, another <hi>Melicerta,</hi> with <hi>Saron</hi> accompanied, had divided the dusky waves) not ceaſing to bruſh the blue billowes, till at length they eſpied a very faire harbour, ſituate between two Rocks, neere adjacent to a very pleaſant Iſland, where grew (in ſeemly ranks) great ſtore of pleaſant trees, laden with fruit, the ground being garniſhed (like another <hi>Tempe)</hi> with all ſorts of fragrant flowers, <hi>Zephire</hi> ſeeming continually to breath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; but no houſe, or humane ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance could they view: To this delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Paradice they directed themſelves, comming on ſhoare exceeding faint, and weary, of whom more hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:66275:58"/>
                  <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The King (being exceedingly enamoured on</hi> Sophronia: <hi>would faine ſeem youthfull, making himſelf monſtrouſly ridiculous. His courting of</hi> Sophronia. <hi>He invites her (hoping to enjoy her) to</hi> Ziva. <hi>She kils him there, and eſcapeth.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou heard before, that King <hi>Clodomer</hi> was become a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>Cupids</hi> Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (notwithſtanding his late loſſe) to whoſe Deity he was now ſo obſequiouſly devoted, that (hoping thereby to appear amiable in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia's</hi> eyes) he caſt off all former gravity, befitting the eſtate, and Majeſty of a King, apparrelling himſelfe in youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full habit, ſhaving away his beard to the very ſtumps, and poudering thoſe hoary haires on his Scalp abundantly, that they might ſeem whitened by Art, and not by Nature; moreover, he put a ſilver hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted rapier by his ſide, and to his band<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrings
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:66275:58"/> he annexed rings of ſeverall forms, decored with ſtones of various hewes; and (that nothing might be wanting to make him every way extraordinary) he often exerciſed his <hi>Genius,</hi> in ruthfull Rimes, melancholy Madrigals, and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Ditties, bewailing the cruelty of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid;</hi> that fit over, he compiled many horrible Hymns, in the praiſe of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe Celeſtiall Feature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The brightneſs of her Haire, the highneſs of her Forehead, the neatnſſe of her Noſe, the handſomneſſe of her Hand, the fineneſſe of her Foot, and the gravitie of her geſture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this fantaſtick dotage of <hi>Clodomer,</hi> was no whit pleaſing to his Lords, nor was it well reſented by the vulgar <hi>(who are ever for the moſt part, glad of all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that may warrant them to think mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their Superiors)</hi> ſome ſaying he was mad; others, that he was a foole; others, that he was no longer fit to govern.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Clodomer,</hi> (though he were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſenſible of the various whiſperings, and repinings againſt him) was ſo wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his fancie, that he could as eaſily
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:66275:59"/> ceaſe to be mortall, as ceaſe to be a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, yet all this while he made no diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to <hi>Sophronia,</hi> only ſome amorous glances often banquetting with her, and ſometimes griping her moiſt palme; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing her lodgings neere his owne, where ſhe was attended, as ſhe had been the greateſt Princeſſe in the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia</hi> perceived (well enough) what wind filled the Kings Sayles, but took not the leaſt notice thereof, ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing diſconſolate, penſive, and deſirous of ſolitude. <hi>Clodomer</hi> would fain have had men to have thought that he afforded <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia</hi> ſuch accommodation, meerly out of love to her inherent vertues, and eminent worth, and not as deſirous to winne her to his embraces: But now, being reſolved to languiſh no longer, but to break the matter unto her (after banquetting, as was his uſuall manner) he led her alone with him into the Privy Garden, where he thus ſolicited her.</p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:66275:59"/>
                  <p> Madam,</p>
                  <p>I <hi>Am ſenſible, it cannot but ſeeme more ſtrange to you, then an</hi> Africk <hi>monſter, hat I, who (by reaſon of my wrongs) am an implacable enemie to</hi> Amandus, <hi>whoſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date hath impriſoned you ſo many weeks, and whoſe rage would have bereft you of life, ſhould implore your ſmiles [aged as I am] and be ſolicitous to winne your love; but ſuch is the all-commanding power of</hi> Venus <hi>Sonne, that except I may enjoy your ſweet ſociety, (though a King) I am the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretch under the Cope; nor can I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, but the ſoftneſſe of your temper, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the worth of my proffer) will prompt you to embrace that candidly, which is by me propoſed fervently.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia</hi> having heard him, burſt forth into a great laughter.</p>
                  <p>I ſee (quoth ſhe) that <hi>Letchery (like the plague) takes in a bloud;</hi> though <hi>Rhoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> Syre (Sir) you are his heire (I mean to his affections) the truth is (ſpeaking far from heart) I am obliged, Royal (Sir) to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66275:60"/> you, in all the bonds of love, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; and (ſince I ſee <hi>Amandus</hi> ſlights me) ſhall proſtrate all is mine to be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of at your pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clodomer</hi> was ſo over-joyed to heare this, that (ſure if he had not loſt them long before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he had now forfeited his wits; but taking her about the waſte, he ſo embraced her, and beſlavered her, that the pennance ſhe endured then, was worſe then the impriſonment ſhe lately ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Clodomer</hi> imagined all Cock-ſure now, and after many aſſurances of his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and entire affection, he beſought her, that they two, with one <hi>Caſtril,</hi> his creature, (a ſlave that for pence would have proſtituted his owne mother, or wife) might take their journey in a cloſe Chariot, to a Village ſome five leagues from <hi>Verona,</hi> named <hi>Ziva,</hi> and there (quoth he) we may have opportune occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to take the full fruition of our loves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia,</hi> though ſhe hated his perſon, more then poiſon; and his love, worſe then <hi>Lucifer;</hi> yet conſented to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him, which was performed the next morning accordingly.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:66275:60"/>
                  <p> The chaſt Lady being put upon this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, (which ſhe accepted, knowing it was in vain for her to withſtand <hi>Clodomers</hi> power) who, in caſe ſhe had given him a deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, [would have procured her certain ruine] had conveyed that morning into her treſſes, her bodkin, which (to avoyd ſuſpition) ſhe had folded up in her curles, over which ſhe caſt a white veile.</p>
                  <p>Arrived at <hi>Ziva,</hi> they were received at a Countrey Farmers houſe (whom <hi>Caſtril</hi> had prepared before hand for that purpoſe) where entring the beſt cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Graunge afforded, after a repaſt with wine, and junkets, ſo haſty was <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer</hi> to have his bane, that he would needs anticipate the approaching night, (like another <hi>Heliogablibus,</hi> who made day his night, and night his day) the Sun ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving yet ſcarce attained his altitude.</p>
                  <p>The chaſt <hi>Sophronia</hi> (whoſe heart hung heavy on its ſtrings) (ſeeming) [willingly to yield her aſſent] the King [having ſent <hi>Caſtril</hi> to <hi>Verona,</hi> with a command to wait on him towards night] entred the baleful bed, <hi>Sophronia</hi> accompanying him,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:66275:61"/> where he ſoon began to ſhew himſelf ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry active; but <hi>Sophronia</hi> (pulling the bodkin out of her haire) with a ghaſtly look, and a troubled voice, riſing up, uttered theſe words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Canſt thou think, thou fooliſh Tyrant, that what I denied thy wicked Son, I will afford thy villanous ſelf, and that I dare yield up that Fort to thy feeble uſe, which all the Warriours in the World</hi> (Amandus <hi>excepted) can never conquer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Clodomer</hi> would have called out for help, but he was ſo amazed at the ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this unexpected carriage from his Miſtreſſe, that he became loſt to ſpeech] and having ſaid this, alſo adding;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bear witneſs, thou Supream ever-living Power, that I am forced to this outragious Act, for the preſervation of my chaſte Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> ſhe ſtabbed him to the heart, who ſtrugling to ariſe, ſhe againe lodged her bodkin in his breſt, which prevented his ariſall, and diſmiſſed his ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Having done this dreadfull deed, ſhe threw the bed cloathes cleane over him, and locking the doore, and taking the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:66275:61"/> key with her, ſhe departed; of whom more ere long.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol</hi> driving his Carre towards the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes, and night ariſing in ſullen miſts, <hi>Caſtril,</hi> (according to the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) arriving where he left his Maſter, finding the doore lockt, imagined the King had not yet enough of ſport, and therefore he went and walked for the ſpace of two houres, in a neighbouring Grove; returning againe, and finding the doore as he left it, he began to call, ſaying, <hi>My Lord, My Lord,</hi> but receiving no anſwer, he grew extreamly perplexed, and began to doubt ſome danger, and therefore he reſolved to force open the doore, which he did; entring, and approaching the bed, ſeeing the curtaines decently drawne, and the cloathes ſtretched at full length, he began to think, the King, and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, being tyred with active recreation, might be both ſound aſleep, and began to curſe his haſty intruſion; but drawing nearer, he perceived the Kings counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance very much altered, of a pale, aſhy, and bloudleſſe hew, and turning downe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:66275:62"/> the cloaths, he beheld him almoſt covered in his own gore, having two wounds, the one on his ſide, the other betwixt his paps; whereat he flung out of the room (like a man diſtracted) tearing his haire, and ſcratching his face, crying, Treaſon, Treaſon.</p>
                  <p>But of the iſſue of this, read more hereafter, for I muſt now returne to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> whom we left in the Flowry Iſland.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The deſcription of the</hi> Flowry Iſland. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus <hi>and</hi> Pallante <hi>(having reſolved</hi> Agenors <hi>Riddle) are received, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by him, in his Caſtle.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have inform'd you, that the noble Knights, <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante</hi> (by miraculous ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance) eſcaped the danger of drowning, and that (with great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty) they at length arrived on a very fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Continent.</p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:66275:62"/>
                  <p> The Species of things appeared ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious round about them, that they were warranted to think they had lighted upon that <hi>Eden</hi> which <hi>Adam</hi> loſt, but they wondred they found no Inhabitants, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelves, that ſo happy a place could not be devoid of thoſe who were appointed to enjoy thoſe benefits, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (who doth nothing in vain) had there prodigally beſtowed.</p>
                  <p>Having gathered ſome grapes, dates, oranges, and pomgranates, (plenteouſly produced in that plat of ground) they ſat them down under an Almond tree, and (aſwell as their weakneſſe would permit) began to refreſh themſelves with thoſe excellent fruits.</p>
                  <p>It was now twilight, neither day, nor night; they had not ſate long, but they might eſpie a comely Knight, mounted upon a ſtately Steed, clad in the habit of a Grecian, (for indeed that Iſland was part of <hi>Grecia)</hi> a great company follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, on horſe-back, (all ſeeming men of worth and quality) who with <hi>Agenor,</hi> (for ſo was the Knight called) had been
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:66275:63"/> hunting of the Badger, who eſpying two men naked (with fruits before them) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a tree, imagined (as indeed it was) that they were ſhipwrack'd on that Coaſt.</p>
                  <p>Amandus, <hi>was tall of Stature, big of limbs, of a ſterne (yet pleaſing) countenance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pallante, <hi>ſomething lower, not ſo well ſet, yet of a more feminine aſpect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their perſons (though naked) gave <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genor</hi> cauſe to think, that they were above the degree of common men, and pitying their calamitous condition, he alone rode up to them, enquiring of <hi>Amandus</hi> (who underſtood the Greek tongue very well, being a man excellently learned) what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident had expoſed him (and his aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate) to ſuch a direfull diſtreſſe; <hi>Amandus</hi> returned him anſwer.</p>
                  <p>That they were Knights of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Polonia,</hi> (for he would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his capacity, and condition) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound for <hi>Spaine,</hi> by the wilfulneſſe of the winds, had their Ship ſwallowed in the mercileſſe waves, and themſelves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (ſwimming for their lives) upon that Continent; adding, that he had a hope,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:66275:63"/> they were throwne among a people, who were acquainted with Civility, and knew how to be hoſpitable.</p>
                  <p>Feare not (ſaid <hi>Agenor)</hi> but I will ſo provide, that you ſhall have entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be fitting Knights of worth, (ſuch as in my eſteem you are) only I feare I ſhall not be able to afford you the courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie I would, for that by a Law, ratified by my Predeceſſors, none may have the entertainment due to adventurous Knights, in my Caſtle, but ſuch as can unfold the Riddle that ſhall be propoſed to them.</p>
                  <p>At this, <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wondred, <hi>Amandus</hi> deſiring him to propoſe his Riddle, for (quoth he) I doubt not but to explain it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> ayde you (quoth <hi>Agenor)</hi> and ſo calling his company un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, he pulled a Schedule out of his pocket (included in a ſilken bag on which (in capitall letters of gold) was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven this;</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:66275:64"/>
                     <head>RIDDLE.</head>
                     <l>Whats that a faire Lady moſt of all likes,</l>
                     <l>Tet ever makes ſhew ſhe leaſt of all ſeeks:</l>
                     <l>Thats ever embrac'd, and affected by her,</l>
                     <l>Yet is never ſeen to pleaſe, or come nigh her:</l>
                     <l>But a poor mans thing, yet doth richly adorn her,</l>
                     <l>Moſt ſerv'd in her night-weeds, does her good in a corner:</l>
                     <l>Moſt cheap, and moſt deare, above all worldly pelfe,</l>
                     <l>Is hard to get in, but comes out of it ſelfe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>To this, <hi>Amandus</hi> (after a little pauſe) anſwered;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Fame, is that which a vertuous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy moſt of all deſires.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet makes it not known that ſhe affects to accrew it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is ever embrac'd and affected by her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For ſhe muſt perſevere in vertue, or her Glory dies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Serv'd in her night-weeds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Ladies that weare their night-weeds come leaſt abroad.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But a poore mans thing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For many of mean fortune attain to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Fame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Richly adornes her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:66275:64"/>
                  <p> For nothing is more excellent in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then vertuous chaſtity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is hard to get in, and comes out of it ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis no eaſie thing, for a Lady ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean her ſelf, that ſhe ſhall be eſteemed vertuous; but being attained, whether ſhe will or not, ſhe ſhall be well ſpoken of.</p>
                  <p>You are witneſſes (quoth <hi>Agenor</hi> to his Aſſociates) that this Knight, in the behalf of himſelf, and his friend, hath reſolved the Riddle. All replying they were.</p>
                  <p>You are nobly welcome (quoth <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor)</hi> to the <hi>Flowry Iſland;</hi> then diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he one of his Train to his Caſtle, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to bring two ſuites of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, with their appurtenances, with two horſes, the one for <hi>Amandus,</hi> the other for <hi>Pallante;</hi> which being performed, they having cloathed themſelves, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mounted, departed with <hi>Agenor</hi> to his Caſtle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:66275:65"/>
                  <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Sophronia, <hi>entertained by the Shepherd</hi> Crates, <hi>and his wife</hi> Phillida. <hi>The deſcription of his Cottage.</hi> Sophronia <hi>becomming a Shepherdeſs, ſings the praiſe of the Countrey life.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ophronia</hi> (as you heard) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made riddance of her Royall <hi>Remora</hi> (in great feare) travailed ſo long as her tender limbs were able to beare her delicate body, till at length ſhe arrived neare a large over-growne Wood, whoſe aſpiring branches almoſt kiſs'd the Clouds; towards which, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting her way, ſhe ſaw where a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd was making melody to his fleecie Flock, on his oaten reed, ſinging this ſong.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus work we Fortunes diſcontent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To behold our merriment.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We harmeleſſe Shepherds do deſpiſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The anger of the Deſtenies.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:66275:65"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>That which makes the Gown man pine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Souldier curſe Wars diſcipline,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Begets our ſolace, no auſtere</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Phalarian <hi>Tyrant is our fear;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Secure content, and quiet reſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No groanes, or cries of men oppreſt;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Age is no trouble, Death but ſleep,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And we till Death, our vigour keep.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia,</hi> with great delight, liſtned unto the Shepherds Song, and approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near him, the good old man thought that ſome Diety, mask'd in a humane form, was making towards him.</p>
                  <p>Hail gentle Shepherd (quoth <hi>Sophronia) Silvanus, Pryapus, Pan, Pales,</hi> and all the Silvan dieties (and indeed, in naming one, I name all) be propitious unto thee and thy faire flock; and heaven (ſaid <hi>Crates)</hi> for ſo was the Shepherd called, give thee (faire Lady) the full fruition of all thy deſires: My preſent condition (quoth <hi>Sophronia)</hi> will not permit me (gentle Sir) to be tedious in my orratory, for that I expect every minute to be ſurpriſed, by a barbarous Earle of this Country, from
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:66275:66"/> whoſe hands I have this day eſcaped (for the preſervation of my chaſte honour) be pleaſed therefore, to afford me an homely ruſſet Coat, in exchange, for theſe gawdy Garments, together with ſhelter for ſome few dayes in thy Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, till this ſtorme be blown over, and to gratifie thy love, take theſe Jewels (of ſufficient vallue, to make thee Lord of all this champion Country) as my gift.</p>
                  <p>For your Jewels (quoth <hi>Crates)</hi> I muſt not, dare not accept of them, <hi>they are the Plague and Poiſon of honeſt mindes,</hi> but if my homely Cottage, may be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the acceptance of ſo divine a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; command it (Lady) as my ſelf, and all I am maſter of.</p>
                  <p>Away went <hi>Sophronia</hi> with <hi>Crates</hi> to his Cottage, which was builded by a bank ſide, at the root of a Sycamore Tree, whoſe broad branches quite overſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſhallow roffe; the Cottage it ſelfe was erected of graſſe Turfes, ſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly contrived, that it ſeemed rather framed by Nature then by Art, being all over of a verdant hew. Entred therein,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:66275:66"/> ſhe eſpied many ſhelves of Cheeſes, and pans of Milke, with large flitches of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con; <hi>Phillida (Crates</hi> wife) was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly abaſhed, to behold a creature of ſuch bright beauty, ſo gloriouſly appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralled, enter her homely habitation, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that <hi>Juno,</hi> or <hi>Latona,</hi> had deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from Heaven <hi>(as of old, when the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of Shepherds, made them worthy the ſociety of the deathleſſe Dieties)</hi> to viſit their humble dwelling: but <hi>Crates</hi> ſoon took off her wonder, informing her the occaſion of her arrivall; then <hi>Phillida</hi> heartily welcomed her, and ſpreading a homeſpun cloth upon an unpoliſh'd Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhe adorned it with Cream, with But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with her choyſeſt Cheeſe, and fineſt Bread, and taking a brown Bowle (bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed out of the body of an Almond Tree) repleated it brimfull of healthfull Sider, <hi>Crates</hi> and <hi>Phillida</hi> (with many congeis and ducks) proclaiming her wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
                  <p>Having refreſhed her ſelfe with theſe rurall Cates, ſhe put off her gorgeous hab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, and atired her ſelfe in a Coat of ruſſet-gray,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:66275:67"/> binding up her golden haire in a packthread Cawle, and putting homely Buskins upon her feet, taking a hook in her hand, ſhe led forth her Sheep day by day, folding them each night, in as ſeemly a manner, as if ſhe had been <hi>Crates,</hi> not <hi>Almonios</hi> Daughter.</p>
                  <p>Exceedingly pleaſed with this ruſtick life, ſitting one day, upon a bank of Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, her Flock grazing by her, ſhe ſang theſe verſes, in the praiſe of the country life.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>While I the glad and ſmiling ground doe ſtrew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In theſe moſt pleaſant Groves, whoſe verdant hew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Allure great</hi> Pan <hi>and</hi> Pales <hi>here to ſport,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Forgetting quite the pleaſures of the Court;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reſting ſecurely, void of ghaſtly feare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How well were I, were my</hi> Amandus <hi>here</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No Souldier here doth wipe his Sanguine Blade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Made drunk with blood, no Lording doth invade</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The poore mans Houſe, or Land; no foule Sedition,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No Edict, Remora, or Inhibition,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vexeth my quiet peace, my Flocks I keepe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Secure, and dreadleſſe of all danger ſleepe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The fruitfull Vine the Poplar tall doth clip,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o bowes his head, ſweet Nectar for to ſip.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The lowing Heards, far off I doe behold,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Feeding on Meadowes all off burniſhd Gold.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My head with mellow Apples I adorne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Peares more ruddy then the bluſhing morne.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:66275:67"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>When</hi> Jove <hi>forceth his Thunder through the Skie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To empt the ſtore of his Artillery,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into a Grove of Bay I doe retire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And reverence (not fear) his noiſe and fire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O happy country life, thrice bleſt they are,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who are contented with their houſhold Lare.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And wrapt in Goats skins, as ſecurely reſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As thoſe that doe on</hi> Tyrian <hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtry feaſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſleep on quilted Down Beds, all the Pride</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Norimberge, <hi>or</hi> Turky <hi>ſought to hide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their glorious nakedneſſe; oh happy Fate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ſtill attends the humble Shepherds ſtate.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Crownes are compos'd of cares, and Honours be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aring Gins of Deſtinie;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The purblind Goddeſſe takes delight to wrong,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>None ſave the rich, the haughty, and the ſtrong:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here without ſhew of feare, ſecurely I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Doe rob the earth of her Embroyderie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Primroſe, Lilly, Calaminth are here,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Violet, Paunſy, Pagle, and Kings-Speare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Smooth Ladies Smocks, with Hare hels, and the Flower,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That cheifly ſpringeth in</hi> Adonis <hi>Bower;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Myrtle, Spiknard, Gowlands, and the Roſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sops dipt in Wine, Oxe eye, the lips of Cowes;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This is the life thats free from cares, and feare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh that my ſweet</hi> Amandus <hi>were but here.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Here leave we <hi>Sophronia,</hi> and look back to <hi>Verona,</hi> and ſee how the rumor of <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domers</hi> death is reſented.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caſtrill</hi> having declared the time when, the place where, and by whom <hi>Clodomer</hi> was made away, the Nobles were ſo farre
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:66275:68"/> from deploring that heavie Accident (being now grown weary and aſhamed, of <hi>Clodomers</hi> abſurd unkingly deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) that they lift up their hands to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, thanking the great power, that had benignly bereaved them of ſo beſotted a Prince; and the common people <hi>(who are ever delighted with change)</hi> ſang Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to Providence, that had taken off their burthenſome Head, without hurt to the Body politick; but neither the one nor the other, had any true cauſe of rejoycing (though <hi>Clodomer</hi> had forfeited the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a King, by giving too much ſcope to his fond loving Lunacie) for the <hi>Girpids</hi> being aſſured that <hi>Amandus</hi> was wandring about the world, and that King <hi>Clodomer</hi> was dead, reſolved to break in peices the yoake of bondage, that <hi>Amandus</hi> had put upon them, and to invade thoſe that had vaſſalized them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:66275:68"/>
                  <head>CHAP. VI</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The deſcription of</hi> Agenors <hi>Caſtle; he declareth to</hi> Amandus, <hi>the reaſon, why he propoſed the Riddle, as alſo, that no Women inhabited there, containing the Hiſtory of</hi> Sinoris, <hi>and</hi> Eugenia, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genors <hi>Kinſman ariving from</hi> Spaine, <hi>declares newes very pleaſing to</hi> Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus; <hi>he and</hi> Pallante <hi>(furniſhed with a Ship, and all other neceſſaries) ſet ſaile for</hi> Verona; <hi>the</hi> Lombards <hi>receive him triumphantly as King.</hi> Sophronia <hi>(having been much ſought after by</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus) <hi>at length diſcovers her ſelfe; the mutuall joy of the two Lovers; the cellebration of their Nuptials, and Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow if my compaſſe, and my card be true, I ſhall ere long, put in at the wiſhed Port.</p>
                  <p>You have heard before, of the ſtrange entertainment that <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> found in the <hi>Flowry Iland,</hi>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:66275:69"/> and that <hi>Agenor</hi> (the Lord of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) courteouſly conducted them to his Caſtle; which was ſcituated on an high promontory, ſurrounded with all ſorts of Trees, ſet in ſeemly rankes, in the midſt whereof, ranne a demi-River, watring thoſe pleaſant plants. The Caſtle was framed all of <hi>Median</hi> ſtone, of Ovall forme, yet ſo vaſt of extent, that it ſeemed a petty City; it was ſurrounded with a Wall of Marble, on which at equall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and of juſt proportion, were an hundred Towers: before the Caſtle lay a Pond (invironed with a living Wall of Eglantine, fed by a Chriſtaline Spring) repleat with all ſorts of Fiſh; in it (moſt lively carv'd in ſtone, by the skill of ſome cunning <hi>Dedalus)</hi> ſat the Rector of the Seas (according to the Poets) earth ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Neptune,</hi> on a Sea Horſe, his Trident in his hand, all his <hi>Tritons</hi> (beſtriding ſeverall Fiſhes) about him, who (by wondrous Art) ſounded their ſilver Trumpets, as they had been living ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrnces, to their great admiration.</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:66275:69"/>
                  <p> Being entred the Caſtle, they found it exceeding glorious; the wals were hung round with cloth of gold, in which were repreſented many famous ancient Stories; the deſtruction of <hi>Troy;</hi> the renowned entercourſe of the Loves of <hi>Hero,</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander;</hi> to the exceeding delight of all that beheld them; they were brought by <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> into a large Hall, paved with Aggats, and moſt richly garniſhed, where intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to ſit downe, he began to ſay as followeth.</p>
                  <p>I aſſure my ſelf (my noble gueſts) that you much admire the reaſon that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned my propoſall of the Riddle, as alſo, (that in ſo happy an Iſland as this) what is the cauſe, your eyes have hitherto not viſited one Female; the <hi>Origen</hi> of both theſe, I ſhall declare to you, briefly, and truly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>About an hundred yeares ſince, there ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as Governour over this Iſland, a Lord of great Fame (my Fathers Father) named</hi> Sinoris, <hi>who had to wife, a Lady nobly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, of great Beauty, and paſsing Wit, named</hi> Eugenia.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:66275:70"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Now it happened, that</hi> Sinoris <hi>became exceedingly intimate with a Lord (of a neighbouring Iſle) called</hi> Alſatia, <hi>[himſelf nominated</hi> Ariaſpes] <hi>they mutually feaſted each other, nothing of note being acted in either Iſle, without the joynt aſſent one of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, their Friendſhip being knit ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it ſeemed impoſsible for the hand of Fate to diſſolve it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Long time they maintained this Amity, till it happened, that</hi> Ariaſpes <hi>became greatly enamoured on</hi> Eugenia, <hi>who, at firſt ſeemed to abhor his lewd deſires, but at length was wonne to let him enjoy that, which ſhe had ſworn to preſerve only to the uſe of</hi> Sinoris; <hi>yet carried they the matter a long time ſo clandeſtinely, that</hi> Argus <hi>could not have diſcovered their private compliance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now it happened, that a Lady of this Iſland, of excellent Feature (a great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantreſſe) was no leſſe taken with</hi> Sinoris, <hi>then</hi> Ariaſpes <hi>with</hi> Eugenia, <hi>and by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and otherwiſe, manifeſted the ſame; but</hi> Sinoris <hi>ſo entirely loved his Wife, (whom he eſteemed ſuperlatively vertuous) that he could not be wonne to hearken to her</hi>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:66275:70"/> 
                     <hi>allurements.</hi> Caſſandra, <hi>(for ſo was the Enchantreſſe called) perceiving her endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were fruitleſs, on a time appearing to</hi> Sinoris <hi>(ſitting alone in ſtudy) told him, that he neglected her love, to doat upon one that was falſe as a falling Star, or glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wornes fire, who ſecretly (yet frequently) cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuted him, by the help of</hi> Ariaſpes, <hi>Lord of</hi> Alſatia.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You may imagine how exceedingly</hi> Sino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris <hi>was amazed to hear this, neither did he give credit to her words, yet with much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, was wonne to make triall thereof:</hi> Caſſandra <hi>(by the power of her Spels) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving transformed him at all points like</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaſpes, <hi>he was eaſily admitted to ride in his own Saddle, which he had no ſooner at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to doe, but</hi> Caſſandra <hi>reſtored him to his own ſhape.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What tongue, or pen, can expreſſe how exceedingly</hi> Eugenia <hi>was aſtoniſhed at this accident: She would have fled away from the preſence of her incenſed husband, but he laying hold on her, ſhut her up in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for ſome dayes, and then (with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all about him) cauſed her to be torn</hi>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:66275:71"/> 
                     <hi>in pieces by wild horſes; the rage he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for her abuſe, being ſo great, that he immediatly baniſhed all women out of the Iſland, ordaining for the future, that none of that Sex ſhould inhabite here; he alſo deviſed the Riddle that you lately reſolved, commanding, that none ſave thoſe who could give the meaning thereof, ſhould have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in this Caſtle, but to be lodged elſe where in the Iſland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> could not chuſe but ſmile, to heare of this ſtrange Law, and that the execution thereof ſhould be ſo ſtrictly obſerved: But (quoth <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus)</hi> how then is this Iſland repleniſhed with Inhabitants, (women being excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitated from among you?) Our wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (like us) ſaid he, have an Iſland of their own (ſurrounded by the Sea) whom once every yeare we accompany, and if men-children be brought forth, we receive them; but if females, they abide with their mothers.</p>
                  <p>But (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> were it not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that this abſurd Law were abrogated.</p>
                  <p>No (quoth <hi>Agenor)</hi> that we dare not
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:66275:71"/> doe; for our fore-fathers being ſworn to it by the vertue of the ſame oath, (we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) all their poſterity are engaged, and obliged ſucceſſively.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And beſides (quoth he) we ave experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally found, that Heaven is exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with the obſervation of this Law; for before this was decreed by</hi> Sinoris, <hi>this Iſland was but indifferently fertile, but now it exceedeth all the Iſlands in the World, for fatneſſe, and richneſſe of ſoile.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fie (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> that you ſhould be ſo groſly ſuperſtitious, to imagine, that the abſence of women, occaſioneth you bliſſe; by the immortall power, I admire, that your fruits are not blaſted, and your Land curſt to a barrenneſſe, that is deſtitute of ſuch celeſtiall creatures, as women are.</p>
                  <p>While they were thus diſcourſing, the Tables were furniſhed with all manner of curious, and luſcious wines, and choyſeſt cates; which while they were feaſting with, behold <hi>Agenors</hi> Kinſman, a young man, of rare beauty, and gallant deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was newly arrived from <hi>Spaine,</hi> (his Ship laden with very rich commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties)
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:66275:72"/> whom <hi>Agenor,</hi> bringing in by the hand, preſented to <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> who ſaluting him (as <hi>Agenors</hi> Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) and underſtanding he came from <hi>Spaine,</hi> beſought him to afford them his preſence a while, and to relate what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence he had received in thoſe parts; who preſently told them, that while he reſided in that Kingdome, Embaſſadours arrived there from <hi>Lombardy,</hi> (Emiſſaries being diſpatched for the ſame purpoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all parts of the world).</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To make enquiry for one Lord</hi> Amandus, <hi>ſometime Generall to</hi> Clodomer, <hi>King of that Countrey (who was dead) for that they reſolved, to make the ſaid</hi> Amandus, <hi>their King; which they were the rather induced to doe, for that the</hi> Girpids <hi>had rebelled, and were now upon the borders of that Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Newes made <hi>Amandus,</hi> and <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante,</hi> look one upon another, like men dropt from the Clouds. Dear Sir (quoth <hi>Amandus</hi> to <hi>Agenor)</hi> I am that <hi>Amandus,</hi> ſo greatly ſought after, now if my <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronia</hi> be but ſafe, I am every way happy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agenor</hi> (ſtarting to heare this) and are
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:66275:72"/> you that <hi>Amandus</hi> (quoth he) whoſe name, Fame ſo delighteth to celebrate; give me your pardon (Sir) that I have yielded you no greater reſpect, and let my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance plead my excuſe.</p>
                  <p>Oh (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> you excell in all nobleneſſe: what think'ſt thou, (quoth <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandus</hi> to <hi>Pallante)</hi> may not Fortune yet make us amends, for all her unkindneſſe.</p>
                  <p>I doubt it not (quoth <hi>Pallante)</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you (Sir) make all the haſt you can into your native Countrey, you know not (deſpairing to finde you) but they may otherwiſe determine then you have heard.</p>
                  <p>But how (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> may wee find Tranſportation? Take no care for that (quoth <hi>Agenor)</hi> I will furniſh you with a winged Veſſel, able Mariners, and all things requiſite for your voyage.</p>
                  <p>You heap favours upon me (quoth <hi>Amandus)</hi> which if I faile to retribute, my ſtrength, and ſenſe, forſake me at once; but dear friend, let all things be in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by to morrow morning.</p>
                  <p>They ſhall (quoth <hi>Agenor)</hi> and having
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:66275:73"/> ſo ſaid, (after he had accompanied them ſome few minutes) he departed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare all things in readineſſe for their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which he punctually performed, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing them a ſtrong, but nimble Veſſel, and Sea-men, luſty of body, and well skilled in marine Affaires.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amandus</hi> and <hi>Pallante,</hi> were lodged that night in a rich chamber, but took little reſt, their thoughts were ſo buſied, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing how to manage affaires for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; riſing early in the morning, <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> had prepared a ſtately Banquet for them, (himſelf honouring <hi>Amandus,</hi> as if he had been the greateſt Prince in the World) after which, he (with a choſen Traine) brought them on Ship-board, where they again, were richly feaſted; and then with teares in his eyes (ſo great was <hi>Agenors</hi> love to <hi>Amandus,</hi> who could hardly forbear, as alſo <hi>Pallante,</hi> to afford him the like womaniſh Reſponſion) he committed them to the mercy of the Winds, and Seas, returning to his Caſtle.</p>
                  <p>So calme were the Waves, and ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable the Winds, (as if, with the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lichian</hi>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:66275:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> Guide, <hi>Amandus</hi> had them in a bag) that within three dayes, they had ſight of their native Countrey: <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> all the way (as indeed he had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) highly extolled the Noble diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Agenor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doth Fame Record (quoth he to</hi> Pallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te) <hi>greater Hoſpitality ever extented hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, by any ſtranger, to unknown Gueſts, then</hi> Agenor <hi>hath manifeſted to us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſhould blaſpheme truth (quoth</hi> Pallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te) <hi>ſhould I not confeſſe it, and ſtrenuouſly endeavour (at leaſt in ſome part) to compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Winds, and Seas proving ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable, that they arrived (without leaſt preturbance) at the Famous City <hi>Verona,</hi> putting in at the Harbour called <hi>Neptunes Cave.</hi> No ſooner was their approach bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted abroad, but the Inhabitants of the City ran unanimouſly to meet him, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him their Lord and King, the Peers and Nobles of that Kingdome reſorting to him with great Joy, of their owne accords, ſwore fealty and homage unto him, conducting him (and <hi>Pallante)</hi> in
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:66275:74"/> great Pomp and State, to the Palace of the late King <hi>Clodomer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Amandus</hi> (though exalted from the dunghill of Affliction, to a Throne of happineſſe) found no content within; nor could he have conceived any comfort, had he been made the Sole Monarch of the World, without the ſociety of his deare <hi>Sophronia;</hi> whom enquiring for, anſwer was made, that (in the defence of her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity) having ſlaine King <hi>Clodomer,</hi> ſhe had ever ſince abſconded her ſelf, none knew where; which cauſed <hi>Amandus</hi> to ſend Inquiſitors all about the Kingdome, to make ſtrict ſearch for her, but all their labour proved to no purpoſe, to <hi>Amandus</hi> exceeding diſcontent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophronia</hi> perceiving by the diſcourſe of <hi>Crates,</hi> and <hi>Phillida,</hi> that <hi>Amandus</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, and received as King, and had ſent Meſſengers into all parts of the Kingdom to make diſcovery of her, was ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with joy, that ſhe ſwouned away, and became dead, but was ſoon recovered by <hi>Crates,</hi> and his wife, who laying her upon an heap of wool, ſo chafed her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:66275:74"/> plying her with warm cloaths, that they quickly reſtored her to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wonted ſtrength; which ſhe was no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>oner Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of, but ſhe beſought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Shepherd <hi>Crates,</hi> to afford her his company to the City, to the which he willingly aſſented: <hi>Sophronia</hi> having deſerted her gowne of grey, and put on her own apparell, made <hi>Crates</hi> her Guide to <hi>Verona.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Arrived there, ſhe directed her way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Palace; ſome of the Courtiers knowing her, ſtrove, which firſt ſhould be the Meſſenger of ſuch happy newes; but <hi>Amandus</hi> hardly credited their words: But <hi>ophronia</hi> being brought unto him, (who was ſitting very penſive under a Canop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f State) he no ſooner had ſight of her, but leaping from his chaire, (let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fall his mantle for haſt) he ran unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>r, and embraced her in his armes, (nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>er of them able to ſpeak a long time for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeping) <hi>for, as the greateſt grief, ſo no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>ubt the greateſt joy, hath the leaſt ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erance;</hi> breathing their ſoules into each other, and enjoying ſuch mutuall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that none, ſave thoſe that have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:66275:75"/> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſſions, are able to expreſſe, they ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o conſummate their long di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ptials, the morrow.</p>
                  <p>Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> as accordingly performed, in great Pomp, and State, befitting the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of a King and Queen. And here, out of the affection I beare to their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, I cannot but afford them this Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Song.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <head>EPITHALAMIUM</head>
                     <l>HEavenly faire <hi>Urania's</hi> Son,</l>
                     <l>Thou that dwel'ſt on <hi>Hellicon;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hymen,</hi> ô thy brows empale</l>
                     <l>To the Bride, the Bridegroome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take thy Saffron Robe, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>With ſweet flowred Marjorum</l>
                     <l>Yellow ſocks of woollen weare,</l>
                     <l>With a ſmiling look appeare:</l>
                     <l>Shrill <hi>Epithalamiums</hi> ſing,</l>
                     <l>Let this day with pleaſure ſpring:</l>
                     <l>Nimbly dance the flaming <note n="*" place="margin">the Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Tree,</l>
                     <l>Only dedicate to thee.</l>
                     <l>Take in that fair hand of thine,</l>
                     <l>Let good <hi>Auguries</hi> combine,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:66275:75"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:66275:76"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:66275:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66275:77"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66275:78"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66275:78"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66275:79"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66275:79"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66275:80"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66275:80"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66275:81"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66275:81"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66275:82"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66275:82"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66275:83"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:66275:83"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:66275:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66275:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:66275:85"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:66275:85"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:66275:86"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:66275:86"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:66275:87"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:66275:87"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:66275:88"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:66275:88"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:66275:89"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:66275:89"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:66275:90"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:66275:90"/>
                     <l> For the paire that now are Wed,</l>
                     <l>Let their joyes be nouriſhed,</l>
                     <l>Lik a Myrtle, ever green,</l>
                     <l>Owned by the Cyprian Queen,</l>
                     <l>Who foſters it with Roſie dew,</l>
                     <l>Where her Nimphs their Sports purſue.</l>
                     <l>Leave th' <hi>Aonian</hi> Cave behind,</l>
                     <l>(Come, ô come with willing mind)</l>
                     <l>And the <hi>Theſpian</hi> Rocks, whence drill</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aganippe</hi> watens ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Chaſteſt Virgins, you that are</l>
                     <l>Either for to make, or marre,</l>
                     <l>Make the Ayre with <hi>Hymen</hi> ring,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hymen, Hymenaeus</hi> ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Amandus <hi>and</hi> Sophronia, <hi>being thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated by holy Church, to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Joy of the whole Realme, all Hymns mixing in one concord. Shortly after, they were in Solemn manner, Crowned King and Queen of</hi> Lombardy, <hi>Reigning long, and happily.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
